<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bad English, yet not Scotch. Mercurius moderatus: or Certain moderate animadversions touchin [sic] a printed paper intytled, An answer to the chief passages in the Scots declaration For prevention and avoydance ofe a new quarre, and sanguinarie combustion. Moderata durant, dissipa gentes quæ bella volunt.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899279</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152813</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77099)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2323:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bad English, yet not Scotch. Mercurius moderatus: or Certain moderate animadversions touchin [sic] a printed paper intytled, An answer to the chief passages in the Scots declaration For prevention and avoydance ofe a new quarre, and sanguinarie combustion. Moderata durant, dissipa gentes quæ bella volunt.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. MDCXLVIII. [1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152813:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152813:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Bad Engliſh, yet not Scotch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mercurius Moderatus: OR Certaine Moderate Animadverſions touchin a Printed paper Intytled, <hi>An Anſwer to the chief Paſſages in the Scots Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For prevention and avoydance dofe a new quarre, and ſanguinarie combuſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moderata durant, Diſsipa gentes quae bella volunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year. MDCXLVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152813:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152813:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Bad Angliſh, yet not Scotch.</hi> Mercurius Moderatus; OR, Certain moderate Animadverſions touching a Printed Paper intytled, <hi>An Anſwer to the chief Paſſages in the Scots Declaration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hel Author dofe thiſt Reſponſion, or reſpoſeine Replye to thels Scotch Commiſſioners Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration touching thels preſent Parliamentarie Propoſitions newly tendered to thel Reingues Majeſtie in thel Iſle, is (as I conceive, and his diſcourſes diſcover) a profeſſed Independent. Yet I intende not to reprove 'im for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as aſſuredly recognoſcein for its geneallitie, it agitates a more moderate and impartial ſpirit then either nour Covenantin Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Presbyterie, or thel Genevan knoxian Combination quich exagitate onely Fyre and Fagot, <hi>id eſt,</hi> rigid and rigorous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, even to extirpation dofe aim other Proteſtant profeſſions and profeſſors, lemſelps onely excepted and preſerved. So (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractein derom thel veritie or falſitie either, dofe thel Independent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152813:3"/>Combinations ſeveral Doctrins, Dogmatizations and practiſes in Religion, and goverment, I intende onely in abſtract, and abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viately, to reprove, or maither onely to rectifye ſum particular paſſages conteined in thiſt Independents Confutation dofe thels Scotch Commiſſioners palpable Partiallities and erroneous Hallu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinations.</p>
            <p>I plainely perceive hee is noe profeſſed, or exact Divine; or at thel maxt, onely filch a one as thiſt pretenceively Reformein anc Reformein Age, ordinarily parturiates, as producein imperfect and abortive Embrions for perfect feitures: as clearely appeares in a paſſage quich hee (yet maxt impertinently to his preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute) alleges, and ſophiſticates in <hi>Bellarmin</hi> concernein a point dofe Roman Catholic, and ancient Doctrine dofe ſupernatural Merit, as vulle particularly appeare in its proper place.</p>
            <p>Except not at my language I intreate you, mut ſuppoſe me in part a ſtranger, in part a Reformer or Refyner dofe nay mathers native Idiome; as havin ſum more facundie, and experiental cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition than I ſucked from her; and ſure it is as approveable for me to Reforme Languages, as others, Religions: peculiarly, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den 'em; and thels matters ley treate, more communicable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations; and ſo for increace in amitie pyr murual converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and commerce; pyr a facilitatein removal dofe iloſe aſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ruſtieities quich nour Angliſh received pyr its commix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture com thel ancient Saxon language; and by expurgation dofe quich, as in other reſpects it is daily perfected: ſo vulle it pye thiſt improvement, conſecute greater affinitie and vicinitie to the Latin, Italian, Spaniſh, and French Languages; and conſequenter more intelligibilitie in relation to thels principall foraine nations. I now paſſe to particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theyr patience</hi> (ſaith thel Replyermeanein thels knoxian Scots) <hi>was ſeen &amp;c.</hi> Thiſt paſſage he verie juſtly reproves in thels Scots: for in reallitie, I conceive ley chiefly exercyſed leyr patience, partly in exſpertein nour preſent paiment dofe leyr mercenary monies now paſs'd: partly in expectein more; More fooles nour Presbyterian party, quich vould purchaſe leyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence in Rebellion at ſo coſtlie a rate; peculiarly cognoscein thels Knoxian Scots ſare as ſildome not perfidious to other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as not loyal to leyr ſoune. Alm quon in thiſt caſe dofe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152813:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>to leyr Native Sovereigne, I vulle not offer to tax 'em, in quich peradventure, ſum vulle irrationally judge it bad fien mins diſhonorable for 'em to prove perfidious than punctual in thel performance of leyr Ingagements, eſpecially dofe leyr treaſonous Covenant, ſince as, <hi>Displicet Dea ſtulta promiſſio:</hi> So conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qvently, more piouſly neglected, or diſſolved than obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thel Covenant, as Scriptures, is uſually expounded as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of men are.</hi> Verie vruely, if you had reſtringed it to thieſts nour novelous Reformation, or Rereformation tymes; in quich as ſacred Scriptures, ſo ley turne Juraments, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants into a noſe dofe <hi>ceare</hi> or wax; quich, and leyr promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lecture dofe thel Bible in ſo manie ſeverall vulgar languages, and Editions, occaſiones ſilch a Babilonian confuſion, dofe hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Errors, and Differences, Sects and Factions as have formerly, and even at thiſt verie preſent, daily pullulate; ey and have ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie influence, even into affaiers dofe State; as it juſtly moved a certaine ingenious and judicious Proteſtant verie appoſitely to vercifie in thiſt inſuein manner.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quee declarid thel Covenants double ſenſe,</l>
               <l>Thel Parliament, or thel Cities Pence?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Accordingly thels Presbyterians, and thels Knoxian Scots de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare leyr Covenant in one ſenſe, thels Independents in an other, ey manie quoe fere Presbyterian Covenanters, have now turned leyr coates playein at faxt and flooſe avith leyr ſo ſolemne, and ſanctified vow; complainein dofe it as forged in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and tou remiſſely, if not perfidiouſly, proſecuted pyr thels Scotch Commanders, as you ſuggeſte; and quich nour then Presbyterian Commiſſioners fere faine to tringue for <hi>falut dofe a benter;</hi> you ſubintende, for defeet dofe an other mine favorable to leyr graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sovereinge and his loyal ſubjects; nor an other more accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able either to thel Presbyterian, or Independant Combinations, ſo you plainly conclude, it fas <hi>forced upon leyr conſciences</hi> to thel ruine dofe am both, Miniſtres and Laies: ſo as thel tyrannie dofe thels Presbyterian Impoſers, I confeſſe, you verie iuſtly taxe for ſeverall other reaſons you alledge for thel iniquitie dofe thel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Covenant, and conſequently for your juſt diſavowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152813:4"/>dofe it, and contrynance dofe a new one more rationall, and ſincere, as you verie rightly ſubjoine, <hi>it was abſurdly hypochri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical to ſweare the preſervation dofe the Kings perſon, quen at ſame tyme a warre is ingaged againſt 'im,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You vruely adde, <hi>the Scots approve onely ſilch Propoſitions as vulle profite Scotland, and Seots in Angland;</hi> ſo to inriche lem ſelps, and depauperate us. I profeſſe accordingly, I ſam not able to apprehend (ulle reaſon, quy nee Angliſh ſhould have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred more Correſpondencie, Contractation, or Confederation com thels Scots, than for ordinarie Commerce. For thiſt is onely to reap <hi>thels ſweet fruits dofe nour fertil Contrie,</hi> as you verie conſiderately ſupertadde: yet pam I not approve your refuſal dofe an amiable Treatie, ſie it at <hi>London,</hi> or at ſum other place, it matters not much; thiſt ſiein thel generally approved meanes for peaceable Accomodations in alm Debates and Controverſies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in thiſt nature, in thel judgement dofe tractable people. Anc ſurely iloſe ſare not guided pyr a peaceable ſpirit (nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to him quoe is <hi>Deus pacis</hi>) quoe avoyde and debarre alm peaceable meanes, and indifferencie for avoydance dofe a new and renewed ſanguinarie Combuſtion in Religionarie and temporal affaires; quich is nour moderate Soveaeignes principal care, and ſolicitude. So as your apprehenſions dofe His Majeſties preſence at <hi>London,</hi> or any oeher place, dofe a new guar pyr it occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſare mearly vaine timorizations, frivolous jealouſies, and onely cavillous tergiverſations as I conceive, peculiarly now, quen thel Citie, and Contrie tou is in thel Armies power, and cuſtodie, and in a ſort, inſlaved to it, quich in ſum degree fas <hi>Herrie</hi> ſeventh's caſe, not nour preſent Sovereignes. Nor yet is it ſo inſiſted pyr thels Scotiſh Commiſſioners, as if one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>London</hi> fere thel abſolutely neceſſarie place for a peaceable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Ey I really conceive, as thel Reingues abſence derom his Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentarie Aſſembly, for cauſes pyr him judged juſt and rational, fas noe juſt cauſe for a civil Combuſtion of quarre: So neither contrarily his perſonal preſence is mearely ſufficient for a Peace, if a pious and tractable affection to it (quich yet in His Majeſty pyr his manie, and yet more inſtantious Adreſſes to thels Parliamenters then ileyrs eo him, is maxt eminently viſible) and mearly perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorie Demandes) meet not avith it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152813:4"/>
            <p>Now if (as you allege I know not quou veritably) <hi>thels Scots were for depoſein him and his,</hi> ley maxt juſtly merite thel odius brand dofe Traitors; peculiarly ſuppoſed his Majeſtie is leyr more native Sovereigne than he is for <hi>Angland,</hi> as joyntly in reſpect hee ſo confidently inſerted himſelp into leyr Protection; quou ever I confeſſe you deſerve ſum Commendation in not denyein thels <hi>Kings dofe Angland had formerly, ſettein aſyde the callein, diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, and peremptorie negative voyce in Parliaments, nothing but would stand well with a Kingly, or Monarchial Goverment.</hi> At thel minſt, if you had ſet a part your exception dofe His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Negative, your diſcourſe had not ſeen ſo totally irrational as thels contents dofe thels quoue new Propoſitions quiſh demande much more, or thiſt and more at thel minſt implicitly. Yet ſure you proceede inconſequently in affirmein, or ſuppoſein excluſion dofe a peremptorie negative voyce in Parliaments, vulle ſtand or conſiſt com Monarchical Government, ſince Monarchie is ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute a Regal Power, as it eſſentially excludes tote neceſſarie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencie ſurpon Parliamentarie Aſſemblies, as clearely appeares in thels Spaniſh and French Monarchies for examplarie Inſtance) ſave onely pyr vay dofe Adviſe or Councel, not pyr conſtreint, as thel verie Etymologie dofe thel name <hi>Monarcha id eſt, ſolus guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans</hi> or rulein alone or ſolely, manifeſtly ſoundes, and declares. So as if you deny your Sovereigne Power for a negative Vote or abſolute refuſal in not aſſentein to, or for his confirmein Laws, propoſed to 'im either even pyr Parliaments, or any other humane Counſel or Aſſembly, you prepoſterouſly deprive 'im dofe his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Supremacie or Supreme Goverment in temporalls, and place it in his Subjects even repugnant to ilat primarie Act pyr quich ley primitively elected 'im for leyr Supreme Governer accordein to thels anciently eſtabliſhed Laws, none denyein 'im a abſolute Diſſent, in Parliaments, or out dofe Parliaments, nor yet prohibitein 'im either to aſſemble, or diſſolve Parliaments quen ever hee judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neceſſarie, or convenient for thel public profit or peace dofe his Subjects in generall; or for preſervation dofe his ſoune, or leyr Honor anc Reputation.</p>
            <p>Anc <hi>a fortiori,</hi> or pyr a more forceable Argument, militates thiſt diſcourſe acounter your excluſion dofe thel Reingues negative Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in aſſemblein, and diſſolvein Parliaments, as much more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152813:5"/>conſiſtent com Manarchial Goverment, and mins prejudicial to thels Subjects, than is his Royall Diſſent for conſtitution dofe anie new Lawes or Statutes; quich veritie now ton clearely elueeth pyr thels preſent lamentable effects, quou requiſite it fas joyntly for thels Subjects and his ſounes preſervation, nour preſent Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne had not only had abſolute Power to diſſolve Parliaments in general, mut even had actually uſed it in diſſolvein thiſt preſent Parliamental Aſſembly, even at its verie entrance, and prieſt tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuations, or tumultuous oppoſitions to its Supreme Governet: quench it almſo corollarily iſſueth quat great reaſon His Majeſtie had not to confirme nor admit, leyr 4. newly diviſed Bills, ſince ley ſo ſorely circumcyſe his Royal Authoritie, and Power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect himſelf, and his Subjects as ley ſcarce leaſhe 'im the very name dofe a Monarch, even repugnantly to leyr ſoune once ſolemn Vow &amp; Covenant expreſly obligein 'em <hi>not to diminiſhe his juſt Power and greatneſſe;</hi> in caſe he voulde agree to leyr Adviſes and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, yet ſubtilly ſubintendein for a deſtructive limitation dofe his ſupreme Prerogative, and Monarchical Power conform to quich leyr extravagant Propoſals, in regard he has (yet maxt rationally) refuſed to deſcende, ley have maxt irrationally and inhumanely reſtrained his Royal Perſon in a manner, as a cloaſſe priſoner, force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably excludein (quich i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prejudicial to 'imſelp, and his Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) alm ſorts dofe Adreſſes, or Applications to 'im in order to peace; even for 'inſelps, and others; ſo totally debarrein him and his Subjects tote humane meanes for a peaceable Accomodation for relief dofe leyr preſent and future oppreſſions, pyr leyr provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to new combuſtions and quarres; even contrary to leyr ſoune precedent pretences, ſo as it is aſtoniſheably ſtrange ley have faces to perſuade thel people, ley deſyre, and labour for peace, and yet directly, and poſitively pyr their ſonne peremptorie Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, profeſſedly, publicly and declaredly renounce alm means poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for attainment to it. Ey yet more amaſeable it is ley vulle offer to contrive a new faſhioned Government, yet aſſuredly cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocein, they have no poſibillity to eſtabliſh either it, or any duta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble peace conform to Lawe, and reight ſenze leyr Soveraigns con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and public Approvement.</p>
            <p>Thels Scots have reaſon to conceive Treaties vulle produce <hi>mutual confidence,</hi> contrarily, you have none for thiſt your Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxical
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152813:5"/>paſſage, namely, <hi>thoſe quoe differ are beſt aſunder.</hi> For if ever aſunder, ley'l meete in a peaceable Accomodation noe ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than mountaines, or ſulnedayes.</p>
            <p>Thels couſenin Scots have now juſt as much reaſon to plead for thel Reings peaceable returne to <hi>London,</hi> and for eſtabliſhment dofe a durable Amniſtie and Reconciliation, as ley baſely, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally refuſed at <hi>Newcaſtel</hi> to admitte 'im into <hi>Scotland</hi> his ſoune native Contrie and Reingdome: quich leyr maxt diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and diſloyal action, I ſam piouſly perſuaded ley now cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially repente, and plainely perceive leyr groaſſe error even in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dofe State. Anc it fas not His Majeſties preſence (nor abſence neither) mut thel perverſe Presbyterian Faction, and leyr tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Adherents, leyr treaſonous averſneſſe fram leyr Soveraigne, quich then cauſed an obſtacle to a peaceable Agreement; nor yet iloſe quoe perſuaded His Majeſtie (as you miſ-imagine) to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract his perſonal preſence: but ileyr malignitie quoe forced him fram <hi>London,</hi> quich has produced thiſt nour inteſtine, and ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Combuſtion; peculiarly iloſe quoe levyed militarie forces; ſenz, anc even directly repugnant to leyr Soveraigns Conſent; anc to thels anciently eſtabliſhed Lawes, as have in had a Campal Armie prefore, or as ſoone as His Majeſtie had a perſonal garde more than ordinarie if my memorie ſayles me not: Yet fare thels Scots inexcuſeable, not only in thiſt, mut even as primarie Cauſers &amp; Prolonguers dofe their native Soveraigns, &amp; our miſeries ajoynt.</p>
            <p>Your rejection dofe His Moderate Majeſties pious offer for a pacifyein Treatie, your deſertin your frathers or brothers in Chriſt thels Knoxian Scots in your mutual Covenant; and former Tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Contractations com or vith 'em, I greatly doubte vulle prove a much more forceable occaſion for a renewed diſnatural quarre, than His Majeſty, or any other dofe his Royal Partie ever adminiſtred for a Comence dofe it, as thel ſequele vulle cleartly demonſtrate, if not maturely prevented. For as thel mutual Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and its contryveance, fas onely pretenceively intended for Peace and Concord: ſo nowe your violation dofe it vulle really conclude in a final renovation dofe nour precedin ſanguinarie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions: Yet is it not my intention to approve your adheſion to thel Covenant as really, not approveable either in its Forme or in its matter, no more than I approve I apts temerations ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152813:6"/>or Vow to ſacrifyſe his dourter quoſe action, yet vulle not excuſe your extravagant inconſtancie in diſavowein ilat maſme quich you ſolemnly, publiquely and generally vowed, and avowed. Ieptes vow and ingagement fas onely prvate, not public; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, not univerſal: yet it is only a diſputable queſtion (or ſcarce ilat) quether he totally performed, or changed his vow in to ſome other matter more acceptable to thel Divine Majeſtie, not ſacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſein his ſilde or childe corporally, mut onely ſacrifyſein her ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to a Religious Inſtitute (as only ſum Catholic Divines out dofe quich <hi>Perkins</hi> thel Puritan picked his conceit as you report it) onely conjecturally opine, quou ever it fas, yet certain it is, Ieptes action, if he really vowed his dourters corporal ſacrification, it fas directly repugnant to thel Divine Commandment <hi>non occides,</hi> now as your Covenantein Vow, fas for a ſanguinarie quarre to thel ruine dofe your native Contrie; ſo in reallitie, it obliges you not to a pious obſervation, mut onely to a penetential retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſavein in caſe dofe an erroneous conſcience: neither yet is it, (if in one part falſe, or erroneous, as in ſum part you vulle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it is) obligatorie; or yet licitouſly performed; even a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a common enemy as you hallucinantly ſuggeſte, even repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to founde Doctrine in Divinitie, ſince <hi>malum ex quocum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> defectu;</hi> no, not even for Reformation dofe Religion. Moreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I diſcover ſum other great difference intreene Ieptes premen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Vow, and thel Presbyterian anc Knoxian Covenant. For his fas evidently peccaminous, as a plain tranſgreſſion dofe a Divine Commandment, as I have now advertiſed, and ſo had an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently approveable cauſe for its exchange into a matter more pleaſein to Deeod: contrarily you have very frivouſely alleged <hi>thel Parliament may change theire Covenant:</hi> ſince according to thel general conſent dofe Orthodox Divines, thel exchange dofe a Vow as directly tendein to a ſpecial honor dofe thel Divine Majeſtie, neceſſarily requires an <hi>evidenter melius bonum</hi> an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently benter, and more acceptable material object to him for its exchange than ilat quich fas formerly offered to his gratious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance.</p>
            <p>Finally, leyr diſcharitable and diſchriſtian Covenant, is ſo much more intolerable in regard it forceth, or forceably induces alm ſorts dofe Proteſtant people even their ſacred Soveraign to imbrace it,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152813:6"/>and not leyr ſoune onely ſects; and to extirpate alm other even Proteſtant Profeſſions, and even ilat one, and onely Catholic one quich has continued pyr a continuated ſucceſſion from Chriſt nour Saviour, and his Apoſtles. So you verie judiciouſly ſubjoine <hi>no better quarrel to contende in than acounter iloſe, quoe vulle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy alm others not dofe leyr Religion:</hi> as thels maxt impious Presbyterians, and Knoxians Scots have mutually Covenanted.</p>
            <p>I accaſionally conceive it is much more rational, and conducent to a Chriſtian peace, and Moderation (iloſe onely Contries excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted quich have euer ſucceſſively continued in one onely Religion) to tolerate alm Sects dofe Chriſtian Profeſſions, than to force Chriſtian people to any one only Profeſſion or Sect, quich has exiſted onely ſince <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Calvins</hi> time. Yet I greatly doubte your <hi>Holland</hi> example, or Preſident is tou large and libertine, as admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein or permittein a <hi>Babylonian</hi> Confuſion dofe <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> as I ſam informed.</p>
            <p>It is a mirement to mee, to heare you pronounce: <hi>The Word dofe God muſt be as the Parliament conceives.</hi> As if Parliaments fere conſtituted Judges dofe thels ſacred Scriptures, or as if Chriſt nour Saviour had conferd anye ſilch power to Parliaments; or yet anye authoritie to judge, reſolve, or determine leyr Orthodox ſenſe, quen as yet your Proteſtant Profeſſors exclame acounter her authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie anc condemne thel Roman Catholic Eccleſie &amp; Church, for onely judgein, or reſolvein leyr veritable intellegence and meanein, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biouſly obſcure places in relation to thel deciſion dofe controvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed matters in Religion; nor yet you vererunde or ſare aſhamed to conferre to a companye dofe laical ſtates, a Judicative power, ſover thel ſacroſanct vorbe or parol dofe Deeod; quich is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly palpable partialitie, mut even blaſphemous preſumtion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and erroneous Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>You ſaye, and verie rectly: <hi>As His Majeſtie is Reingue or King dofe Angland, thel Parliament dofe Augland ſare as apt or fit Judges in framein Lawes for his happineſſe as the Parliament of Scotland.</hi> Yet ſam I ſure it has not appeared hitherto, either thel one or thel other really intends his precedent happines, much mins, anie increaſe dofe it in anie one new Law or Ordinance, mut mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leyr mutual indevores onely tende to abridge &amp; diminiſh his precedently injoyed happineſſe, in forcein 'im to endure no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152813:7"/>diſpatigement in his hereditafily poſſeſſed Monarchical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, greatneſſe, Royal Dignitie, and Honour, as tou cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears even to forraine Nations, and States; and to ſuggeſte thel contrarie, is in realitie as much as if one vould offer to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade mins judicious or mins cautious people, it is a point of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral happineſſe to ſie reſtrained, and abaſed. Now for thel Scots particular, as you hence conſideratedly conclude, <hi>Noe neede has Angland to be inward to Scotland;</hi> ſo I vehemently exopte for his Moderate Maieſties, and his Reingdomes formerly continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted felicitie, nour Parliamentarie Convention had never, intermixed leyr Councels com thels Knoxian Scots. <hi>For, hinc ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lachrymae,</hi> dofe thiſt Scotch Miſt, have iſſued as fyerie Meteors, alm nour Combuſtions, miſchiefes and miſeries quich now nee ſuffer, and ſare to ſuffer more, if not maturely prevented pry a pacifyein Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodation, and Reſtitution dofe nour Soveraign and his Royal Familie to leyr eſtates in leyr ſeveral degrees, and conditions.</p>
            <p>You alledge <hi>the Scots proceedings in Ireland, tou much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourein the Rebelles, and at thiſt time in Treatie avith 'em.</hi> Yet cleare eiſuffe it is, thel once Presbyterian Parliament (for in thiſt ſo clear a caſe, I refuſe not to juſtifye thels Scots action in part) pyr leyr notorious neglects in leyr Supplyes and payments promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and repromiſed, have forced thels Scots in <hi>Ierland</hi> for leyr ſoune ſafetie to complye com thels Ireiſh Catholies, and thel Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Clergie, as you pleaſe to ſtyle thel Ireiſh Tranſacters. Anc conforme to thiſt, ſure his Majeſties action, in caſe hee had ever firmely tranſacted com his Ireiſh Subjectes for an Attonement, (as yet in reallitie hee never fid) hee had nor remained ſo condemnable as thels Knoxian Scots, in regard he contryved not thiſt Accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his ſoun peculiar intereſt, nor yet as a Subject, mut a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne mearely for thel generall Intereſt dofe iloſe his remainein Proteſtants, as expoſed to a total ruine and deſtruction, if not in thiſt peaceable manner precautioned and diverted</p>
            <p>You confeſſe, <hi>you take that libertie</hi> (in Religion I ſuppoſe you ſubintende) <hi>quich in your judgements is according to the mynde dof God, and dare maintain it by argument and Scripture.</hi> Yet I deſire you ſeriouſly to reflecte, you have not on in thels great multitudes dofe Sects and Sectaries, quich now ſo generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound; quich vulle confeſſe its diſabillitie to maintaine its Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matizations
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152813:7"/>pyr Scripture, and Argument, not obſiſtem, you vulle not denye alm or manie dofe lem for groaſſe errors, or plaine Hereſies. You knoe thels heretical Arrians for example profeſſed to defend leyr Hereſie pyr pure Scriptures and ſcriptural argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, even to a peremtorie rejection dofe tote Catholic Roman Tradition.</p>
            <p>Thels Scots allege <hi>thel Reingue is adverſe to the Covenant.</hi> Hence you verie interpretatively, yet verie probablely, if not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falliblely conclude, hee dubſt not ſie <hi>King ofe Angland; Scotland or Ireland, unleſſe hee vulle take the Covenant;</hi> you ſubintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte ſure, accordein to thel Knoxian Scots and thels Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans votes. Yet ſure you falſely inferre hence thel non neceſſitie dofe a perſonal Treatie. For even this maſme peremtorie De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde for his Majeſties enterin thel Covenant, neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers a large debate previous to his entrance, ſince thel Covenant conteines manie ſeveral branches. In thel reſt concernein thel Reingues Impriſonment, or reſtraint, your ſuppoſition is falſe quat <hi>he would indoubtedly chuſe rather to end his dayes in thel Iſle he is in, then to vive in anye ontward contents in London or anye other his houſes, deveſted dofe his Government.</hi> For liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is ſweete, and you ſare not ſo irrational as once to apprehende His Majeſtie (as neither anye other private perſon) had not mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have his libertie even ſenze his Government, than neither his libertie nor his government as now his caſe ſtandes.</p>
            <p>Touchein thels Scots Allegation <hi>to haue nour Armie diſbanded,</hi> iley havein a formed Armye lemſelves, you verie excellently, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly, and forceablely redargue leyr palpable partialltie. Ey if iley at thiſt verie preſent tamper com <hi>France,</hi> as you ſuperadde; it fere maxt impolitique follie in us to diſſolve nour Forces at their requeſt, or motion; contrarily, it fere more reaſon, and rational ſafetie for us to recruite, and increaſe 'em. Yet if you content lem in monye matters, I remain eaſily perſwaided ley vulle not much trouble lem ſelps for reſtorement dofe thel Reings Majeſtie for tote leyr ſpeciouſly pretended zeale toverſe 'im. For if ley have vended 'im once, ley vulle venture to vende 'im once more, I greatly doubt.</p>
            <p>Anc I occaſionally advertiſe, I penſe Roman Recuſants (not obſiſtein leyr great impoveriſhments, eſpecially dutein thel tymes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152813:8"/>dofe thiſt longue Parliamentarie Seſſion) and for avoydance dofe new Revolutions and ſanguinarie Combuſtions, vulle not refuſe to pay thels Scots leyr 200000 livers ſurpon Compoſition for leyr libertie dofe conſcience in Religion; quich is noe unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, nor unſeaſonable requeſt, eſpecially in a tyme quen alm (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptein thels rigid Presbyterians) generally conſpire in a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Indult for tender conſciences, ley havein indured as longue &amp; tedious a perſecution, as thels Jewes in leyr Babylonian captivitie, if not yet longuer; ſo as thiſt once tranſacted, and inacted, thels Purſuivants Penſion, and leyr future troubleſome Proceedings pight or might conſequently ceaſe.</p>
            <p>You preſently ſubjoyne, thels Scots ſubintende onely thel In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent part dofe thel Armey quen ley allege, ley expected to have it disband at leyr receſſe, and returne into <hi>Scotland.</hi> For as you verie veritably reprove 'em, if thel Army continuein had ſien or been Presbyterian, ley vould never have moved, or expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its diſſolution.</p>
            <p>You almſo, vruely reject another objection manie tymes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in thiſt, and other occaſions, namely quat <hi>thel Armye</hi> fas or <hi>was raiſed contrarie to his Majeſties minde,</hi> not percauſe nour Angliſh Parliament alone, as nor thels Scotch Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alone, ſenze leyr Sovereignes joynt Authoritie ſare proved Judges dofe thieſt, as you inſinuate: mut in regard his moderate Majeſtie never precedently complained dofe thel Independent Armye: no for contrarily, I ſam confidently perſwaded, if he had remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſtant, and favorably affected to thel Independent Part dofe thel Armye, and Parliament, and not tou favorable, anc indulgent to his Scotch Contryhomnes, or leyr nation, he had not ſuffered ſilch reſtreint, anc diſcontent, as now hee indures: quou ſie it, I now perceive pyr certain Intelligence, hee is not ſo much curbed, nor confined, nor ſomuch diſcontented as thel vulgar report di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulges; cauſed (as I conceive, and augmented, if not invented, pyr thel Presbyterian and Royal Parties, to render thel Independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Combynation odious. Ey in particular, I greatly deſire thels Mercurian Pamphleters vould uſe more diſcretion and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in leyr Relations and jearein corrozives; and cognoſce for certain leyr tranſported zeale for his Majeſties Reſtoration, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the impedites, or at minſt, retardes it than advances it, in tou
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152813:8"/>much exaſperatein ileyr mynds in quoſe onely power now it is (I mean thel Independent Armie) peaceablely to reſtore 'im to his Royall Rights and Honour dofe quich thel Presbyterian, and Knoxian Faction have formerly deprived 'im; quoe contrarily if he had affectionouſly adhered to thel prementioned Armie, he had gained thel Cittie and thel Parliament ajoynt, ſince now ley ſare amboth, at thel Armies command; peculiarly conſidered, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie once voluntarily declared, thel Armies Propoſals ſtood more for a firme, and dureable Accomodation, than thel Parliaments Propoſitions precedently tenderd at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court ſo as I now verily conceive his onely apte meanes for a peaceable Attonement and his ſoune Reſtorement, is to reconcile his formerly gracious affections to thel Independent Partie, jointly in thel Armie, Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and Cittie, perſuadein 'em to diſſolve leyr Covenant com thel Presbyterian Combynation; and ſo accorde a part for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> onely. Alias His Maieſtie pyr his conjunction com thel Scots alone, vulle neceſſitate 'imſelp to a new quarre, and ſo render 'imſelp odious even to his precedently benaffected Angliſh Subjects, and forfeite thel Intreſt he had in leyr aſſiſtance; pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly to thel Independent Combynation, as accountein thel Knox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Scots leyr maxt mortall enemies, and oppoſers; quoe have ever as generally diſproved His Majeſties tou great propenſions to thel Scoth nation (if not more) as anye other Faction or Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation now, or precedently in his Dominions.</p>
            <p>Touching <hi>thel aſſurance thels Scots pretonde ley had from thel Angliſh Parliament, for his Majeſties ſodaine libertie,</hi> I eaſily conſente to you, ley had none in reallitie, as hath now clearly appeared pyr contrarye effects. Ey thels falſe Scots ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving leyr native Sovereigne voluntarily, and in confidence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to leyr future protection in his diſtreſſe, dunctil hee had peaceably accomodated his affaires, ley remained obliged (even accordein to leyr ſoun public profeſſions in leyr printed papers) pyr thel verye law dofe Nations, not to deliver 'im, eſpecially to iloſe quoe ley aſſuredly cognoſced for ſo impiouſly affected to his Royall perſon as ley had precedently voted 'im priſoner to Varrick Caſtel, quence yet more cleerlyappears thels Scots maxt diſnaturall treacherie to leyr natural Soveraigne, particularly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, as you reightly advertiſe, <hi>thel Parliament would not have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152813:9"/>refuſed his return into England,</hi> even in caſe he had paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Scotland for thel preſent, as he greatly, and juſtly deſired for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yoydance dofe his Angliſh Enemies violent malice ſo as thels Scots loyaltie quich ley ſo ſpeciouſly pretexet, is onely juſt as great to leyr Prince, as to leyr profit, not one jot more; as famous for contendin diſhonorein, deſtroyein leyr Sovereigns, as you very ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably conclude thiſt your Paſſage conforme to hiſtorian relation. For really, leyr diſloyaltie to his preſent Majeſtie; and his Angliſh Reingdome, is tou eminently apparent in Covenantein, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutein this nour diſnaturall combuſtion, and ſanguinarie guarre quich has cauſed his, and his maxt loyal ſubjects almaxt total ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, as in an other occation I have ſufficiently convinced.</p>
            <p>I profeſſe, I conceive no juſt, nor judicious cauſe (you neither) quye thel Scots vould meddle com or with el continuance dofe nour Angliſh Aſſembly; eſpecially, ley havein ſate ſo longue, and ſo ſpente thels peoples monies to ſo ruinous effects; nor yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vein concluded leyr fooliſhly projected Innovations, either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force dofe argument, or forceable Reſolution pyr Scriptures; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther public or private ſince for eſtabliſhment dofe leyr Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Government ley uſe onely a poor ſnekin <hi>ſeemes</hi> for leyr aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion dofe it, as in leyr preamble to it ley ſare faine to confeſſe in leyr Tractate intytled <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> ſurrevence, yet is it not much material quou ley proceede in ſo ſuperfluous, and diſneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a buſineſſe, ſo thel charges fere ſaved.</p>
            <p>Thels Scots complaine <hi>thel Presbyterian Religion anc Goverment is not ſetled.</hi> To quich you verie acutely reſponde thel ſettlement dofe Religion and government, <hi>muſt be (as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant curnes or runs) according to the word of God:</hi> quich you finely gloſſe to ſie or bee thel Scotch Presbyterie, ſince in reallitie ley deceptorily obtrude to leyr ignorant Auditories leyr ſoune novellouſly diviſed commentations, for thel pure vorbe dofe Deeod, and thel onely Evangelical veritie, as alm other moderne Sectaries ordinarily preſume; yet is it in ſubſtance, leyr ſoune falſe doctrin deaured com thel ſpeciouſly plauſible niename dofe thel divine parol or vorbe; ſo is thels benſt <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> (in leyr uſual notion) noe other than leyr ſoun <hi>Scotch Keale,</hi> and Genena roots as an ingenious Proteſtant finely ſtyles 'em, lat is leyr ſoune knoxian Raphſodie; and rigid Calvinian Government,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152813:9"/>practiſe in perſecution alm other Chriſtian profeſſions ſauein one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leyr ſoun pretenceively reformed confraternitie.</p>
            <p>Thels Scots yet more largely alledge, and reprehend a libertie granted to alm Formes dofe adoriſhip or worſhip, and opinions, in lieu dof leyr unical knoxiſme, or Presbyteriſme. Yet I perceive you abſolutely deney thel Parliamentarie Aſſemblye concedes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to alm opinions or dogmatizations; quich I charitably crede to ſie ſo; nor is thiſt a direct vay to blaſpheme, except abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; diſtorted. No, you ſubioyn verie adviſedly, it is intrith Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants diſputable (conſequenter not puniſhable) <hi>quich is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, or an Idolatrous act.</hi> Yet Orthodox Divines indiſputablely reſolve conforme to ſacred ſcriptures, and its verie Etymologie, Idolatrie is <hi>latrie</hi> or divine adoration dofe an Idol, or ilat quich is not really Deeod; quence ley infalliblely inferre thel honour quich Roman Catholies exhibite to Chriſt nour Sainours image, or to thels images dofe his beatified ſaints, is no reall Idolatrie, as onely conteinein a certaine honourarie reſpect (eſpecially as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to thel repreſentation dofe ſaints precyſely) infinitely inferior to diuine culture, or adoration, and is in realitie a feigned Idolatrie onely pyr leyr peruerſe Adverſaries, ſo conſequently not deſervein puniſhment, nor prohibitable as Idolatrie is. Anc yet more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is &amp; infallible in practiſe, Roman Catholics ſare totally ſecured from alm note dofe Idolatrie, as longue as ley onely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſacred images or pictures according to thel ſenſe and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dofe leyr ſoune Catholick Roman Chirch, quich (as cleerly appears pyr its Doctrine delivered in thel Tridentine Councel for one) has ever maxt cautiouſly avoyded, &amp; deteſted alm Idolatrie and ſuperſtition tou <hi>Drum pantur licet Nouatores noſtori Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriani haeretici &amp; Knexani quoque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For blaſphemye, it is as I conceive properly and ſtrictly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a contumelious parol or action exerciſed a counter thel Divine Majeſtie, yet in a more largely received ſenſe, it imports any ſilch other contumelie or reproch as reflects to anye his rational creatures (eſpecially his glorified Saints, and Angels) in quich Deeods Divine Majeſty as leyr Creator notably aluces or appeares. For as honour and reverence is due to thels prementioned Angles and Saints, not onely for thel peculiar relation, ley have to Deeod omnipotent leyr Author, and Sanctifier, quoe is honored in ilem,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152813:10"/>and in their honor (conforme to eximious Saint <hi>Augustin</hi> fynely expreſſein it, <hi>in Petro quis honoratur miſi ille defunctus prono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi>) mut even for ilat ſupernatural dignitie ley injoye in lemſelps: ſo is ſilch inferior Religious honour and reverence, verie lawda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blely, and religiouſly exhibited to 'em pyr us quoe ſare greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to 'em in ſanctitie and glorie: and ſo contrarily it is damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reproche or revile 'em, and even inth or within thel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe dofe Blaſphemie in its total latitude. Thels Eliſabethians, Epiſcopals, and Puritans eſpecially, have violently perſecuted us Roman Catholikes thieſts 80. anths or years, and more, for a mearely feigned Idolatrie, and pretended Superſtition; and have cruelly butchered nour confeſſedly vrue anointed Preiſts, even di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrarie to ilat Divine Precept <hi>nolite tangere Chriſtos me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os,</hi> for a Law founded in a faigned, anc falſely ſurmiſed Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for quich, and for his public Proteſtations (real or feigned) for execution dofe thels maxt injuſt penal Statutes inacted acoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter us, I greatly doubte <hi>Rex Charles</hi> quondam, and his Elizabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than exorated Epiſcops now ſuffer leyr preſent oppreſſions as juſt Judgments. Yet for my part (&amp; thel maſme charitable ſenſe I perceive generally in nour Roman Catholics) I ſam cordially ſorie for leyr ſufferings, &amp; really exopte, &amp; deſyre ley had ſien in thel number dofe iloſe dofe quich nour maxt miſericordious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt Jeſus pronounced his Divine ſentence: <hi>beati miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordes quoniam ipſi miſericordiam conſequentur: &amp; beati qui perſecutionem patiuntur propter juſtitiam, &amp;c.</hi> not for Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; dofe quich ſort dofe more miſericordius Chriſtian people, I charitably confide, thels more moderate Independants vulle, at thel minſt, admit us into ſilch a moderate Compoſition as vulle greatly eaſe us in nour accoſtomed perſecutions; quich yet nee humbly requeſte ſurpon anie conditions in nour power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, for redemption dofe nour dayly vexations: for as <hi>judicium ſine miſericordia illi qui non facit miſericordam:</hi> So <hi>ſuperexal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat miſericordia-judicium.</hi> Thiſt, Itimorize, vulle fall foule to His Majeſtie, for his tou zealous imitation dofe his Pather &amp; his Pathers Profeſſion, in defence dofe Proteſtancie, in quich he has tou much dofe <hi>Amon,</hi> &amp; tou modic dofe <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conforme to thiſt libertie for tender Conſciences (not for alme opinions as thels Scots falſly object ſay you) quich if anye
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152813:10"/>other profeſſions injoye, ſure thels Roman Catholics quoe have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſo rigerous &amp; longue a perſecution ſo conſtantly, &amp; unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, as (onely a verie pew or few ſlike tainted fruits have drop'd derom thel arbe or tree dofe nour eclirch, ley have now greateſt reight to injoye it in quyet poſſeſsion (eſpecially havein it at ſo keare rate) as is offered) &amp; not to ſie forced to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue anye longer tyme ſubter ſo inſupportable a yoke as you in an other reſpect, verie forceably redargue thels cruel Scots ſo much preſſein for thel Presbyterian Government, quoe yet vould have condenmed for a point dofe Tyrannie to have leyr Contrie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to thel Common prayer ſervice; or leyr French Compart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Religion, namely thels Calvinian Hugonotes to have ſien, forced pyr leyr Soveraigns to thel Roman Religion, as you joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuperadde; to quich you yet more excellently ſubjoyne, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealein to thel Univerſal Chriſtian orbled <hi>quether there be much dofe reaſon for a Prince to compell his people to be dofe his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi> Touchein quich, you verie judiciouſly challenge 'em to prove it fas dithen or given 'em <hi>imediately from Christ or Deeod, mut (as you ingeniouſly ſubjoyne) if hamered out dofe thels heads of an Aſſembly dofe Scots &amp; Angliſh Divines, noe reaſon compulſion be uſed quen infallibilitie canot be made good. Thels Jewes, Chriſt, his Apoſtles never compelled, &amp;c.</hi> So accordein to thiſt your Judicious &amp; equitable diſcourſe, no reaſon nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is uſed in perſecutein Roman Catholics peculiarly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they profeſſedly maintaine &amp; demonſtrate leyr Religion ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſively deſcends fram Chriſt Jeſus, &amp; his Apoſtles pyr a viſible pedegree dofe Paſtors &amp; Doctors, or Deachers, quoſe names nee ſare able to produce; quich contrarily not anye other profeſſors ſare able to performe.</p>
            <p>Thels Scots more ſover ſuggeſte <hi>Preſbyterie is limited for a tyme.</hi> Not to relate thel reſt you ſufficiently rejecte thiſt obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in ſayein, <hi>Perdone Angland if they take not Preſbyterie ſurpon Scotlands nude or naked recommendation, its poſſible for us (as to perſecution) to leap out dofe the fryein pan into the fyre;</hi> you intende out dofe perſecutein Epiſcopacie into more rigorouſly perſecutein Presbyterie. Then ad thels Scots: thels <hi>Miniſters ſare to exclude none fram thels Sacrament, ſavein whoe thel Parliament judges meete.</hi> In reallitie thels Scots have reaſon in thiſt exception, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152813:11"/>quat Scripture have you for a laical or temporal Aſſembly to Judge dofe ſpirituals, or dofe ſpiritual matters, as is thels vrue Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, except you ſubintende thel one is as ſpiritual as thel other, <hi>id eſt,</hi> neither thel one nor thel other in reallitie. Let thel Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriſts or Presbyterian Aſſemblie produceus ſum Scripture quy either thels Presbyterians, or Presbyterian Parliament onely dubſt have thiſt libertie or priviledge, to debarre or admitte to thel Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, &amp; yet noe power for others either to admitte, or repel others from it: no ſacred text appeares for thiſt Partiallitie.</p>
            <p>Thels Scots preſſe yet more cloſely, <hi>Thel Parliament allows not alme Ordinances.</hi> You Reſponde, &amp; Reply thel Parliament allowes alm quich ſare <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> Yet you ignore not thels ſacred Scriptures conferre noe filch Authority to Parliaments as is to judge quich is a Divine Ordinance quich not ſo. Thiſt fere a ſtrainge <hi>hiſteron Proteron,</hi> or prepoſteriouſly to ſet thel equorſe or horſe prefore thel Cart, vulle onely a peuſament, or Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie <hi>thinck,</hi> as you frivouſly inſinuate, ſatisfie &amp; ſecure tender Conſciences either in thiſt or any other caſe? No ſure, in thiſt you hallucinate verie palpably and groaſly.</p>
            <p>Touchein <hi>toleration dofe Sects,</hi> you referre thels Scots to your ſoune falſe Hiſtorie (if any ſilch either falſe or vrue, is extant in nature) or if you intende to apply it to matters dofe Faith quich ſare equally as infallible as thels ſacred Scriptures, or as thel Divine Spirit leyr immutable Author. Yet for matters dofe practiſe or manners, theiſts pae ſumtymes admitte alteration conforme to, <hi>Tempora mutanter, et nes mutanter in illis,</hi> ſo in thiſt onely ſenſe, Eccleſiaſtical Councels, even Orthodox, put in or put out (as you phraſe it) very rightly &amp; conſideratly, ſince moral actions leyr circumſtances once Changed, ilat quich fas once virtuous, &amp; laudeable, turnes vicious, &amp; illicite. For example, it fas once (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thels Apoſtles days) not peccaminous &amp; offencive to abſteine from ſangue, &amp; ſuffocated or ſtrangled: yet now, &amp; longue ſince, neither thel one or thel other is mins than offinnous or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous &amp; damnablely Judaical. Now if, as you preſently adde, you tolerate Sects, onely for temporal reſpects, or for civil Peace, and if not conſiſtent com yours, you vulle ſuppreſſe'em; now thiſt is not to ſuffer 'em accordein to ſacred Scriptures preſcript (as you uſually expounde) nor yet for eaſe dofe tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152813:11"/>if as you intimate, for temporal Cauſes alone you vulle ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe 'em; nor differ you greatly derom or from thels verie Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians &amp; Knoxians in thiſt particular, quome yet you profeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemn for perſecutein alm others into their own profeſſion, &amp; Government: you ſuperadde you voulde have none debarred derom or from ſcritein or diſcourſein acirc or about alm Religions ſo ley ſie or do noe hurt, for preventein quich, you promiſe care vull ſie or be had; you ſubintende ſure hurt to thel ſtate, as you preſently expreſſe. For in ſcritein, diſcourſein, or printein either, to reſtreine it, fere in a great meaſure, to reſtreine libertie for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences in Religion. Only I conjoyne com you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provein thels Scots preſumption to printein <hi>Angland</hi> ſenze vlle licence, or authoritie, eſpecially in ſo incendiarie a ſenſe and ſtyle as they uſe, for a new combuſtion; yet ſcritein Controverſies in Religion in Latin you except verie rationally, and diſputations tou, &amp; you ſubjoyne yet more rightly it <hi>fere or were ſad, if nee pight or might not diſcourſe ſinthout or without baniſhment, or impriſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thels Scots complaine thel Directorie pas'd ſo long tyme &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, is put apart, quich leyr Complaint, you in an effectual Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemme, verie fynely confute argumentein in thiſt mode or forme; either thel Aſſembly has fone or done its part, or not. If they have not, let them finiſh it, publiſh it, &amp; a vay to their charges. If ley have finiſhed it, <hi>quy ſare ley yet here? Ley fere called onely to adviſe &amp; preſent.</hi> To quich I ſuperadde avoyde leyr Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, or Aſſembly dofe Aſſes; ey ſodainely let 'em pack, &amp; ſie vone or gone. For ley conſume thels Subjects monies in vaine, &amp; proſe or worſe: ſo it is great pittie ley ſare ſuffered to linguer &amp; loyter any longuer, 4 ſhillings a day for ſo manie miniſterial prators to ſpende only in bucolies or bellitimber, is no trivial expence, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapidation, ſover &amp; above leyr pinguedinous Benefices, &amp; Lecture penſions. <hi>Comodunt panem impietatic, et bibunt vinum iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</hi> [Prov. 4.] I ſeriouſly doubte nee ſharme never have peace &amp; quietneſſe dunctil nour new Weſtmonaſterian Monkes (I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende thels Rereformein Presbyters) ſare thence removed, &amp; leyr irreligious Convent deſtroyed. Anc in regard the Presbyterian Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters (as tis reported) obtained part dofe leyr Conqueſt pyr Prybes and Treacheries, I rationally ſuſpecte ley vulle not proſper.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152813:12"/>
            <p>Thel Scots objecte <hi>Faſts ordained for extirpation dofe Hereſies, and Sciſmes. Non ſatis capio.</hi> I ſcarce conceive your Reſponſion to thiſt in regard I conceive you put it in queſtion, quether Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies &amp; Sciſmes ſare ſo percauſe <hi>contrarie to thel Vorbe, or Word dofe Deeod or God.</hi> For quou vulle you have Hereſies cognoſced, if not cogdoſced as contrarie to Faith conteined onely in Deeods parol or divine Revelation, ſcript or not ſcript, quich is thel Rule dofe Veritie, &amp; counter Rule to falſitie. You allege danger ſince <hi>everie one has libertie to judge.</hi> Yet thiſt reaſon is a mearly ſenze reaſon ſave onely in iloſe Profeſſions quich vulle have everie Ignaroe a learger &amp; expounder dofe ſacred Scriptures; nor your proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in remittein thiſt to thel Civil Majeſtrate is one jot more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. Is it not conforme to ſacred Scriptures, or divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or Vorbe, or to natural Reaſon either, for Politic States, to reſolve, or yet diſpute matters dofe Faith or Religion, &amp; its contrarie Hereſies, or Sciſmes, or frame or eſtabliſhe ſpiritual go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Thiſt is no Ordinance nor Order dofe Chriſt nour Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious: No, for ſo ſayes great Saint Ambroſe <hi>Chriſtus non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit Eccleſiam ſuam Regibus aut Imperatoribus, ſedſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, &amp; bonus Imperator intra non ſupra Eccleſiam eſt.</hi> No, for thiſt ſpiritual charge fas committed peculiarly &amp; namely to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; his continual ſucceſſers; ey thel contrarie is a dangerouſly injuſt uſurpation directly repugnant to thel ſacred Text, <hi>Tu es Petrus</hi> &amp;c. Or if thel contrarie fere even as much as coulorablely conforme to thel ſacred Bible, yet quou more proper, firme, &amp; infallible Authoritie has thel Spiritual &amp; Eccleſiaſtical State for thiſt purpoſe. Ey it is maxt prepoſterous for civil Potentates, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to declare or determine, or yet authoritatively to advyſe <hi>quat ſhall ſie or quat not,</hi> (as you verie conſiderately ſuggeſte) in matters quich ſare not civil nor politic, mut mearly ſpiritual. For, <hi>quae medicorum eſt, promittunt medici; tractant fabrilia fabri.</hi> Vulle you have an Artificer judge dofe ilat quich perteines not to his traide? ſo you vulle verifye or render ilat vulgar Adage tou applyeable to yee: <hi>Ne ſutor ultra crepidam. In hoc non laudo.</hi> If thels ſubjects dubſt obſerve thels temporal Majeſtrates decrees in Eccleſiaſtical &amp; Spiritual affaires, it totally confounds thel dooe ſpathes, or ſwordes, namely thel ſpiritual &amp; temporal, &amp; quite deſtroyes libertie in Religion for tender conſciences, quich I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152813:12"/>you have not reflexively conſidered.</p>
            <p>I conceive thels Scots ſtand for thels authoritie dofe thel ſupream Majeſtrate even accordein to thel Covenant ſubintellectein pyr thel ſupreme Royal Ruler namely thel Riengues Majeſtie, Touchein quich, you affirme thel Parliament offers his retume ſurpon ſilch termes <hi>as ley conceive ſafe,</hi> &amp; boond <hi>or good:</hi> quich is verie vrue, if you mentally reſerve: <hi>bood for 'emſelps not for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thels privileges dofe nour Angliſh Parliament, &amp; thel peace dofe thel Angliſh Reingdome, I eaſily conceive, thel Scots have ſien or bien as great violaters as anye other: ſo you verie courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly recognoſce your obligation to <hi>Scotland</hi> in Relation to <hi>Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> Yet I profeſſe, I cognoſce not for quat, except you vulle accompte it a favour in 'em to have notoriouſly concurred to its deſtructive diſturbance, ſo as if now they would redreſſe us, it is not in leyr power ſenze an increaſe dofe nour miſeries pyr a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed guarre and yet a greater combuſton than ever; nor ſcarce ſo, ſave in caſe ley prevayle &amp; ſo conquer us, yet more to nour coſt &amp; diſhonor; dofe quich I have an ancient prediction in my cuſtodie. <hi>Quod Deus omen avertat.</hi> Ey Angland has ſien at ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive charges avith 'em, &amp; even ſenze ulle exſpectation dofe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit redoundein derom or from ilem. Angland has payed ſoundly for it Scotch favor, if favor you vulle name it.</p>
            <p>Thels Scoth adjoyne, <hi>many Sectaries &amp; leyr Adherents pyr leyr doctrins &amp; actions offer violence to leyr Reingues perſon &amp; Authoritie:</hi> I confeſſe I vould greatly approve thiſt in thel Scots if it fere ſinceare &amp; impartial, &amp; leyr ſoun diſnatural, &amp; diloyal actions had not proved thel contrarie, as joyntly you &amp; my ſelp have ſufficiently convinced iley &amp; thels Presbyterian Combination, &amp; leyr concovenanters have in preached, &amp; practized thel maſme violence quich now ley ſpeciouſly pretended to condemne in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; indevorein to Reforme forſoth Religion, &amp; Monarchical Authoritie even perforce dofe ſanguinarie Armes: &amp; ſo ſare ley as pittle or little excuſeable in leyr actions as in leyr Dogmatizein Principles; as having longue ſince agreed com thel Presbyterin Faction, His Majeſtie ſhart have no other Authoritie than accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dein to thels Scotch or Knoxian circumciſion. As for violation dofe <hi>everie Article</hi> conteined in thel Covenant, you juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152813:13"/>it for a vaſt falſitie impinged, &amp; injuriouſly offered to thels Independent Aſſociation, &amp; concludein thel maſme pyr divers Inſtances, as concurrein in thel puniſhment dofe Delinquents, and maintainein thel Doctrine dofe Scotland accounter thel common Enemie &amp;c. Yet in thiſt particular ſure you ſare not verie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to your ſoune Profeſſion, quich is noe approver dofe Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Doctrins &amp; Governement.</p>
            <p>Thels maſme Knoxians charge you for Cauſers dofe Factions, as <hi>challengers dofe thel name of Saints &amp;c.</hi> quich you rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dargue as not proved, mut onely charged, quich abundantly ſuffices for confutation dofe ſo frivolous allegations, as ley relate to Faction. Yet I com your licence, adde concernein thel challenge dofe ſanctitie pyr thels Independent Profeſſers; It is as impoſſible for 'em to ſie really Saints except ley have one &amp; thel maſme Judgement in Religion, <hi>id eſt</hi> one &amp; thel maſme Faith, as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe Deeod ſinthout or without Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. quich Faith is one, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. So if Proteſtants have not thiſt one Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Faith &amp; Religion (as now even at thiſt preſent, it more clearly appeares pyr thels greater numbers dofe multiplyed, &amp; yet multiplyein Sects ſubter one Proteſtant name) ley ſare really no Saints for alm leyr prayers, meditations, preachins, or other patts dofe exterior ſanctitie; let 'em not deceive lem ſelps, or others, mut mark diligently ilat judicious and veritablely certain ſentence pronounced pyr eximious Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſutably to thels prerecited Scriptures <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi non eſt vera Fides</hi> (quich accordein to thel ſacred Scripture is onely one) <hi>non poteſt vera eſſe juſtitia.</hi> Thel reaſon dofe quich you have deliverd in thel renowned Tridentine Councel [<hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.] fynely definein <hi>Fides eſt fundamentum, &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix omnis justificationis,</hi> &amp; conſequently dofe tote ſupernatural ſanctitie or ſaintly actions &amp; virtues. For ſanctitie is an effect dofe juſtification, as juſtification it ſelp is a partial effent dofe Faith. Yet I confeſſe iloſe quoe have ilat onely one vrue Faith &amp; its Profeſſion, quich thel ſacred Scripture require pae have thel denomination dofe Saints, in quich ſenſe thels Apoſtles in leyr ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Epiſtles, uſually terme iloſe Saints to quome ley direct 'em, alm quou peradventure ley fere not alm really Saints in virtuous actions, &amp; converſation, as for example, clearly appeares in thel Inceſtions Corinthian &amp; others. I marvelle you reflected not quou
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152813:13"/>manie Hereſies, Heretical Errors, &amp; Sciſmes, &amp; other groaſſe offences ſare in Judgment quen obſtinacie is ad oined eſpecially; conforme to thel Apoſtle Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> verie cautelous advyſe: <hi>Hereticum hominem devita—cum ſit proprio juditio condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> Tit. 3.</p>
            <p>Yet I perceive thels Scots pietie for toleration in Religion ſtreches it ſelp ſo much as <hi>not to have pious &amp; peaceable people troubled, if in alm theints ley pa not conforme to thel Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an government ſo it ſie or be not deſtructive to leyr publick Kerk, or (Knoxian) Kerk order;</hi> quich I confeſſe vould not prove diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational, if ley lem ſelps vould not partially reſerve thel determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation dofe thiſt libertie to leyr ſoune Judgments precyſely not ſufferin anie, not dofe leyr ſoune profeſſion, to have anye part in thel diſcuſſion, &amp; final Reſolution dofe it. Alias I doubt it vould reſolve into a thient dofe no thient, as leyr ſubſequent limitation plainly ſubjoines, namely ſilch <hi>a Toleration as is conſiſtent com thel Covenant.</hi> For if thiſt rigid vow doubſt ſie obſerved, quich expreſſely requires one uniforme Reformation or Rereformation excludein tote Neutralitie in its proſecution, then adieu tote con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable toleration for anye Profeſſion ſavein leyr ſoune Genevan Knoxiſme, or Scotch Presbyteriſme.</p>
            <p>Quou you applye <hi>Bellarmins</hi> doctrine to thiſt your purpoſe, I profeſſe my ſelf totally diſable to divine, as if he had aſſerted <hi>thel beſt and ſafeſt vay to ſalvation, is to ſie or bie juſtifyed pyr thels merits dofe Jeſus Chriſt alone:</hi> quen as thiſt maxt eminent Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall (quome alm novel ſectaries mortally envie for his ſollid confutations dofe leyr hereſies &amp; heretical errors in his ample &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte Deciſions dofe controverſies) has neither more than quine or 5 voolkes or bookes dofe Juſtification, (not 12 as you verie falſly ſuggeſt) nor yet has he thel paſſage you cyte for <hi>juſtification by works onely</hi> (as you fradulently dictate) mut for juſtification pyr faith as pyr thel foundation dofe ſupernaturall Juſtification joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pyr faith &amp; other virtuous habits infuſed pyr Deeod, mamely divine faith, ſpairance or hope &amp; charitie in nour prirſt or primarie Juſtification &amp; pyr other virtuous &amp; meritorious actions in nour ſecond, or ſecundarie Juſtification; in quich yet he profeſſedly maintaines faith &amp; thels divine merits dofe Chriſt nour Saviour to ſie thel principal cauſe &amp; foundation dofe tote nour boonde operations; or vertuous actions &amp; merits, as neceſſarily ſuppoſein
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152813:14"/>'em, &amp; proceedein derom em, &amp; not otherviſe performable pyr us then pyr divine grace &amp; aſſiſtance: ſo as your application dofe <hi>Bellarmines</hi> paſſage to thiſt your diſcourſe, is not onely totally impertinent, mut even a meare ſophiſtication &amp; corruption dofe his doctrine &amp; parols; quoe has not alme theiſts quich you falſely relate, videlicet: <hi>the beſt &amp; ſafeſt way is to be juſtified by the merits of Jeſus Chriſt alone: mut theiſts others: propter incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem propriae juſtitis, ac periculum inanis gloriae, tutiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum est fiduciam totam in ſola Dei miſericordia, &amp; benignitate reponere, cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 3. quich paſſage he has not (as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſorily impoſe to your ignorant Peruſers) touchin merits in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral quich he profeſſedly aſſerted, &amp; cleared derom thels noveliſts diſſound exceptions &amp; cavils: mut onely dofe <hi>ſpes ar fiducia in meritis non collo canda,</hi> as in thels very tytle dofe his ſempt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cleerly expreſſes; ſo as ſure you had no ſpectacles either for your noſe or your minde; quen you ſo falſely, and ignorantly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed thiſt maxt eminent, &amp; orthodox Divine. I really conceived thels Independents had carried more honeſt mindes, yet now I perceive ſum dofe lem have no more ſynceritie than thels Puritans or Presbyterians in traducein nour Roman Catholic Divines, &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie. One famous Puritan (if not more) namely ſir <hi>Humfry Lyne</hi> falſified thiſt maſme place a longue tyme paſſed: ſo it appears thiſt leyr corruption &amp; traducement (as manie other quich I have longue ſince obſerved in peruſein leyr tractes) paſſeth as it fere pyr a continued tradition derom one to another, ſo I conclude thel maxt Doctrined Cardinal verie Catholicly maintaines merit performed pyr divine concurrence, &amp; ſupernatural auxiliation, &amp; efficatiouſly confutes &amp; confoundes thel contrarie heritical error: Yet verie adviſedly advyſeth us not to confide in nour ſoune me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in regard everie particular Catholic is not aſſured he has <hi>talia merita</hi> (I uſe <hi>Bellarmines</hi> phraſe) ſilch merits as are ſufficient for atteinement dofe eternal ſoluation. Conforme to Catholic ſenſe, thel maſme Author has another Propoſition in thel maſme chapter. <hi>In bonis meritis quae veretalia eſſe compertum ſit, ſiducia aliqua collocari poteſt, modo ſuperbia caueatur,</hi> quich I ſuper a bundly adde thel more plainely to confounde an impertinent, &amp; cavelous ignaroe in matters dofe Divinitie: Yet ingeniouſly concedein thiſt ſcripter is verie ingenuous in conſuting thels Scotch Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152813:14"/>abſurdities &amp; temeratious hallucinations. Touchein thiſt point dofe ſupernatural merits mellifiſlaus Saint <hi>Barnards</hi> adviſe is moſt ſafe &amp; ſound <hi>merita habere cura, habita data noveris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thel reſt quich thels Scots objecte in leyr preſumptious declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is chiefely invectiues a counter toleration in Religion, except it ſerve for leyr ſoune knoxian palats; &amp; greatly preſſein for thel performance dofe leyr Covenant, in leyr ſoune ſenſe onely, yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly cognoſcein it is now canceld in leyr acception &amp; ſenſe onely: I adde, if as you concede, you intende not to reſtore his Majeſtie to tote ilat quich formerly he had <hi>de jure,</hi> then I doubt it vull proue in you <hi>ſummum jus ſumma injuria,</hi> or prorſe, to deprive 'im dofe it, particularly his negative verdict, even quether you condeſcende to a Treatie or not, or if his Majeſtie has power to excepte at thel Parliaments Propoſitions, or at ſum matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in 'em (as you volontarily confeſſe) ſo has he much more power to rejecte lem totally, in caſe he judgeth none dofe thels matters conteyned in 'em conduceable to himſelpe, or his Loyal ſubjects, mut thel plaine contrarie, for ſo thel conceſſion dofe leyr total collection, vould prove much more prejudiciall then onely ſum particulars. Eſpecially ſuppoſed you joyntly confeſſe <hi>thel Parliament is not about to put Laws ſurpon 'im ſithont or without his conſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if tote thiſt be really ſo, I have not I profeſſe abilitie to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend or imagin quon thel Parliamenters indeauour to deprive 'im dofe his negative voyce, quich is onely his Royal diſſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom iloſe particular Articles, or bils quich his Parliament pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundes to 'im for his conſent; quen he maturely perceives 'em prejudical to his Royall Perſon, Honour, or Authoritie, as ley re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to his Subjects Protection, profit, &amp; proſperitie. Anc if you once concede 'im his negative in eſtabliſhment dofe new Laws, ſurely it vulle prove noe more preiudical to Parliamentarie Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to concede 'im tote thel reſt dofe his Royal Reights or Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties quich de jure he has ever hereditarily poſſeſſed. Ey if abuſes in his Government ſare cauſed pyr his Favorites (as yet you onely conjecturally ſurmiſe) ſince even now quen he has none ſilch in his preſence, he firmely perſiſts in his ancient principles dofe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in quich yet if humaine frai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltie ſuppoſed, faults ſare incident, frame you lawes to remove thels accidental cauſes, yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152813:15"/>not ſo as to deſtroy or notablely to alter thel fundamental power. For ſure you vulle not aboliſhe your Bible per cauſe manie doſt you corrupteit &amp; abuſe it either in text or ſenſe or in thel one &amp; thel other. I conceiue thel Royall Authoritie is <hi>fundamentum fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentorum,</hi> ſo if you deſtroy it, you deſtroy alm fundamentall Laws and Gooernement anciently uſed in nour contrie, neither is it vrue, or pyr you proued, mut onely gratis affirmed: Nour Rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues in leyr hieſt power pould or could not raiſe ſouldiers, or monie to defende lem ſelves, or ſubiects ithout or without Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, remainein euer in thel nature of ſubiects (peculiarly quen ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated derom leyr Soveraign) as I inſtance in thel Parliament dofe <hi>Fraxce,</hi> have power (as tou clearlie eluceth in thiſt preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamental Aſſemblie <hi>dejure or defacto</hi> to leavie Militarie Forces (yet not forced to it) for leyr defence, &amp; yet thiſt accounted or reputed conforme to thels Laws, contrarily thel maſme not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thel Soveraigne not onely for his ſoune defence, mut even for defence &amp; protection dofe thel greater &amp; nobler part dofe his ſubiects, then ſure nature it ſelpe is in thiſt turned prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterouſly partiall, quich ever has uſed to confer everie one an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant power to defende em ſelps: nor as I clearly perceive, fere you able to produce any one inſtance in law or generally received cuſtome for thiſt your temerariouſly efuted poſition.</p>
            <p>It now tou clearly appeares thels preſent Presbyterian part dofe thiſt Parliamental Conjunction have a deſigne conteined in leyr 4. new Propoſitions or Bills to deprive leyr Soveraigne dofe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently poſſeſſed power to governe and protecte his ſubject ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordein to iloſe ancient Lawes quich preſcribe 'im thiſt ſupreme Authoritie, at thel minſt, as longue as ley deteine 'im reſtreined derom tote communication com iloſe in quoſe power it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore 'im either pyr Treatie, or pyr anye other meanes, or dunctil he conſenteth to leyr peremtorie demaundes for a notable dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution dof his Monarchical power to governe and defende his ſubjects; as his Majeſtie precedently injoyed pyr heditarie ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: quich I effectually conclude in thiſt ſubſuein Sylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme. Thiſt onely premiſed quat to deprive a Monarch dofe his negative vote or Reſolution for eſtabliſhment dofe new Lawes, is not to reforme or regulate, mut to ruinate his Monarchie, &amp; much prorſe or worſe than to <hi>diminiſhe his juſt power &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152813:15"/>quich yet leyr Scotch Covenant expreſly prohibits; in quich thels Knoxian Scots ſare indenyablely obnoxious for alm leyr ſpecious pretexts, as havein privately profeſſed, &amp; combyned com thels Presbyterians to reduce nour moderate Monarch to thel ſtate dofe ſilch pettie Reings, as is thel Reing of <hi>Denmark, &amp;c. Itoſe deſtroy Monarchye quoe</hi> ſo diminiſh a Sovereignes Regal power as to deprive a Monarch dofe his Power to governe alone independently ſurpon his ſubjects, more then pyr mode, or vay dofe meare adviſe, or counſel in <hi>rebus arduis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians force leyr Soveraigne to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne dependently ſurpon his ſubjects more than pyr mode dofe adviſe in <hi>rebus arduis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians deſtroye leyr Rengues Monarchie or Monarchical Government.</p>
            <p>I have added in my argument purpoſely <hi>more than pyr mode</hi> or vay <hi>dofe adviſe</hi> or counſel, in regard Parliamentarie adviſe &amp; counſel, as neither anye other involves anye neceſſarie acceptance in an abſolute Soveraigne or Monarch, mut onely quen hee 'im ſelp judgeth it neceſſarie either for thel preſervation dofe his ſoune Royal perſon, Honor, &amp; Authoritie, or Protection, &amp; profit, or greater conveniencie dofe his ſubjects in general quich (as denotein onely a certain voluntarie congruitie in thel Sovereigne to accepte his ſubjects advyſe or counſel, is not repugnant to Monarchical power, or to governe alone (as thel verie Etymologie dofe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie clearly imports and ſoundes) noe more, ey much mins in Parliaments than in other inferior counſels, than it is repugnant to Monarchie for a Soveraigne, or ſupreme Governour to uſe thel adviſe dofe his counſel dofe State, or anye other private, or publique direction in his Government. Neither is ſilch Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie Adviſe or Counſel in vain, (as ſum inadviſedly &amp; vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly objecte) mut contrarily verie conducent and profitable, as even general, &amp; daylie practiſe, clearly demonſtrates.</p>
            <p>So if, as it is generally reported, your final Project is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a new faſhioned Forme dofe Government in State affaires (for matter dofe Religion I voluntarily omitte to meddle in it in regard I remain aſſured it matters not much quich dofe ſo manie ſeveral Proteſtant Profeſſions carries thel preeminencie in Rule or Government, anie or none) I maxt humbly intreate you feriouſly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152813:16"/>&amp; cordially to ponder in primis, quether to turne Monarchie into Anarchie or Ariſtocraſie (dofe quich ne have at thiſt preſent a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaverie taſte in nour ourthes or mouthes &amp; ſtomacs) or into anye other Goverment, vulle ſie more profitable to thels ſubjects, &amp; honorable to nour Nation, than thel Monarchical Goverment, anciently eſtabliſhed &amp; uſed; &amp; quether thiſt chainge is certainly ſo, &amp; not onely in thel Judgment, or Dictamen dofe thel minor &amp; mins noble parti dofe thels ſubjects? II. Quether thiſt total alteration in thel ancient Goverment, is not a notorious Everſion dofe thel Primarie Fundamental Lawes, and directly repugnant to thel ſubiects ancient libertie, and honorarie privilege to have a Monarch for thel ſupreme Governor, &amp; not a Parliament onely? III. quether thiſt intended or proiected change is not a much greater innovation &amp; vulle not cauſe much greater &amp; more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous preſſures to thels ſubiects than anie other quich thiſtverie Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentarie Aſſembly ſo greatly &amp; violently condemned in others, &amp; in other occaſions. Finally, quether thiſt maxt notable Inova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not much above or totally ſuperates not thel Power dofe Parliaments, (eſpecially ſilch as thiſt preſent Parliamentarie Aſſemblie quich onely ſum part dofe thel ſubiects approve) quich in reſpect &amp; relation to leyr Soveraigne, ever remain in thel na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dofe ſubiects quether diſ-iunctively or coniunctively conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; &amp; ſo ſare not dofe thiſt ſuperlative Power in quoſe execution ley committe a totally prepoſterous Deordination, directly rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to reaſon, &amp; ſacred Scriptures a joynt; quich expreſſely injoyne 'em to obey leyr ſuperiours, &amp; remaine ſubiect to em. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedite Praepoſitis verſtris &amp; ſubjacete illis,</hi> Heb. 13. &amp; more in particularly to leyr Reigues; <hi>Regi quaſi precellenti.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. <hi>&amp; Regem honorificate</hi> in thel maſme Chap. 17. Finally in general, ſervants ſare commanded to ſie ſubiect to leyr Maſters even fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ones, ibidem 16. <hi>Servi ſubditi eſtote Dominis &amp;c.</hi> quich <hi>a fortiori</hi> is intended, &amp; extended to Reingues as to chiefe &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Maſters.</p>
            <p>Neither is it ſatisfactorie, for you to allege thels Hollanders Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, as a model dofe thiſt your new attempt; quoſe caſe is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely different not onely in regarde ileyr oppreſſions (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fame reporteth) pyr leyr Spaniſh Governers, particularly thel Duque of <hi>Albe;</hi> but even in reſpect thels Hollanders, alm
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152813:16"/>or maxt dofe 'em unanimuſly conſpired in ſubtractein leyr obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; ſubjection, &amp; change dofe thel Goverment for removal dofe leyr general grevances incomparablely more greevous than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie nour Parliamentiſts, or even malice it ſelpe is able really to excogitate acounter nour maxt moderate Soveraign; for quoſe Monarchical Honor &amp; Authoritie, thel greater &amp; more noble &amp; conſciencious part dofe his Subjects, have firmely, &amp; loyally adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him. Anc iloſe contrarily quoe have not aſſiſted, mut op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed leyr grrcious Soveraign quoſe moral virtues &amp; integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie even forraigne Nations admire) peculiarly ſum dofe thels No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; thels Presbyterian or Puritan Citizens: thieſts for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainein a civil Combuſtion, &amp; ſanguinarie quarre, &amp; thels others for aſſiſtein in thel then Presbyterian Parliament, I voulde not greatly condemne thel Independant Partie, &amp; Armie if ley remove thels preſent Nobles derom their Places anc Votes in thel preſent Parliament now continuein, as a maxt juſtly merited puniſhment and reproofe for ſo diſloyally treatein him dofe quome ley received leyr Titles dofe Honor &amp; Poſtoes dofe profit; &amp; leyr defence dofe thel Presbyterian Faction &amp; Scotch Knoxians quich oppreſſed his moderate Majeſtie; quich leyr action of ſo grooſſe ingratitude, deſerves ſum notorious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, as a juſt regarde dofe leyr diſloyal follie; quoe yet have ſtood onely for ſtales or blacs, or meare Cyphers to thel more Authoritative Commons in thiſt preſent Parliamental Aſſemblie; in quich leyr inferious in place, have commanded 'em as maxt baſe &amp; cowardly daſtards ſufferein thels Commons to commande, &amp; ſuper-rule them in alm occaſions, and ſo, as they have juſtly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieted leyr negative voyce, ſo ley have juſtly merited a total ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheare for ever ſiitein in anye future Parliaments, mut-to ſie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected &amp; ejected as mutil ſervants, &amp; Apochryphal Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Semblely thel Presbyterian Part &amp; Partie dofe it, greately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not onely diſarmein in lieu dofe havein thel Milicie anie lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guer in leyr power, mut even to have Citadles or Forts Royal, avith Preſidiarie Souldiers in 'em; erected, &amp; maintained even at leyr ſoune charge, to curbe &amp; ſuppreſſe leyr treacherous ſuperbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to intercepte leyr future Rebellions, &amp; inſolent Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; In caſe ley ingage a new for Presbyterie, or refuſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152813:17"/>com thels Independent Partie for an honorable Reſtitution dofe leyr Soveraigne: yet Iacciablely advyſe thels Independents, ley parte not avith thel <hi>London Milicie,</hi> &amp; Tower, remittein lem to thel Cities cuſtodie or managerie, for ſo ley ruine leyr Armie, &amp; leyr ſoune Combination; &amp; ſo ley vulle prevente lem in ſo hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous &amp; loyal an action as is leyr Soveraigns Reſtorement to his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie &amp; Royal Dignitie. Let not either thels Presbyterians or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents ſo much either preſume or deſpaire, ley have not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſecuritie either for leyr actions, or leyr perſons except ley have thel Royal Milicie in leyr poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>I ſuperſede thel reſt compryſed in thiſt paper, quich in ſubſtance is not much more than thel Author has ſufficiently redargued in ſubſtance in his Precedent Paſſages, ſettein a part leyr Scotch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils &amp; colloguein flatteries dofe thel Citie; &amp; frivolous complaints accounter nour preſent Parliament, ſince it fas expurged derom or from thel infection dofe its corrupt members; quich as now not purely Presbyterian, it greatly diſtates leyr Knoxian Pallats. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I advertyſe in general, it is thel Presbyterian, &amp; Knoxian Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for curtallein, &amp; circumcyſein Monarchical Authority quich produces timorizations, &amp; jealouſies dofe foraine Armies, &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions; even as leyr perſecutions in Religion for Conſcience produce dangerous effects; as ſembly vulle thel Reigues ſover cloaſe, &amp; Rigorous Reſtraint, ſo aliene it is to tote peaceable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: For as thel ancient Adage tou exactly inſtruct us, <hi>qui nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um emungit, elicit ſanguinem.</hi> I really conceive as alm thieſts violent proceedings acirc or about his Moderate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties preſence have totally, or chiefely iſſued derom thel Presbyterian Partie yet remainein in part, in thel preſent Parliament even ſince it (onely partial) expurgation, even yet at thiſt preſent ſurreptitiouſly prevailein in manie occaſions: ſo even directly repugnant to leyr ſoune deſignes and councels (for, <hi>comprehenduntur in conciliis quibus cogitant</hi>) ley ſlyke as a cloaſly circumſtant <hi>antiperistaſis,</hi> greatly augment thel peoples affection joyntly to leyr Reingues Royal perſon, and to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Goverment; quoe yet if ley pould or could have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed a no-Reingue or no-King at an eaſier rate than is leyr partly preſent, and partly imminent ruine and deſtruction, ley vould peradventure not have appeared ſo averſe to admit dofe a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152813:17"/>change, as now plainely perceivein, or greatly doubtin, if ley change, ley change for thel proſt. Anc infalliblely thel extreame rigor dofe thel preſent Goverment, forceably impelles liberouſly natived people to abhor democraſie as much as demonicraſie, quich I greatly admire nour grand Statiſts clearly perceive not. Yet I vould not have Presbyterians to applye to 'em ſelps my precedent corroſive Propoſitions ſavein onely for ſo longe or ſo farre as ley continue refractorie to leyr gracious Sovereignes abſolute, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegral Reſtitution, alm other conditions or limitations excluded. For if com tractable &amp; illimited termes, ley vulle condeſcende &amp; peaceablely concurre com thels Royaliſts &amp; others His moderate Majeſties loyal ſubjects (I meddle not avith his Religion) to his precedently injoyed Monarchical Honor, Authoritie, &amp; Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aitie ſenze ulle diminution dofe his Power, &amp; Greatneſſe, ley ſhart ſie ſure to have <hi>Mercurius Moderatus</hi> for a ſpecial Favorit.</p>
            <p>It is now demonſtratively clear (at thel minſt <hi>a poſteriori</hi> or pyr thels effects) thels Presbyterian &amp; Knoxian Covinanters have not ſo ſanguinarily contended, onely for preſervation dofe Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in Religion, Parliamentarie Privileges, thels ſubjects libertie, quich yet more particularly appears now in his Majeſties Impriſonment or violent Reſtreint for refuſein to aſſent to leyr extravagant demandes touchein thel Milicie, aſſemblein or diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vein Parliaments &amp;c. quich in him fere tou irrational to expect. If thel hereditarie Sovereigne dubſt not continue in his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I conceive iloſe deſerve to have it, quoe have ventured maxt for it, <hi>id eſt</hi> thel Independent Armye, &amp; Combination, not thels Presbyterian Parliamenters quoe have not perded, mut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed leyr particular eſtates. Let us not create nour ſelps new conquerers pyr a renewed guarre &amp; combuſtion, to governe us either according to thel Scotch or French Lawes, as <hi>Guilliam</hi> thel Conquerour governed us according to thels Lawes dofe <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye;</hi> let us maither indure thels faults (if anye conſiderable) dofe nour preſent heriditarie Sovereigne than thel much greater rigor dofe Forainers. You have him now in thel douſe or houſe dofe correction, yet preſume not to correct his ſacred Perſon anye longuer <hi>(ne aliquid deterius vobis contingat)</hi> mut onely his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in Goverment. Thiſt vulle prove a ſufficient, &amp; competent precaution for future occaſions, &amp; in thel reſt perdone him, as he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152813:18"/>vule perdone you; uſe ſum moderate condeſcenſion as hee uſes com you, &amp; ſo juſtice &amp; peace vulle amiablely ſalute one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, alias it is totally impoſible for 'em ever peaceably to incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For eure dofe exulcerated vulnerations &amp; ſores, let us mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe lenitives than corroſeives, as more agreeable to thel na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural diſpoſition, &amp; greater part dofe his people. Yet I confeſſe, I aurde or dare not totally excuſe His Majeſties actions in thieſts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: For alas, if for his tou great indulgencie to his Scotch Nation, he had not ceaſed to proſecute his Knoxian Scotch guarre, he had maturely &amp; opportunely prevented thieſts nour Angliſh miſcheefs &amp; miſeries, &amp; ſo ſecured 'im ſelp &amp; his loyal ſubiects, as thel then Puritan Faction vould never have had power (thels Scotch Knoxia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s not confederatein com 'em) to prevail acounter thel Royal &amp; Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Partie, nor yet audaciouſneſſe to attempt a diſturbance dof nour formerly floriſhein peace. Since it now manifeſtly appears leyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual indevours durein thiſt Presbyterian Parliamentarie Conventio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, have tended pyr violent &amp; ſanguinarie Armes to mainteine &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance leyr ſoune Combination onely, &amp; to ſubdue alm others (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thel Independent partie tou, if thel Independent Armye had not pyr a maxt gallant ſtratageme opportunely prevented leyr per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Project) quich vould not conforme to leyr new Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Reformation &amp; Goverment jointly in Religion &amp; State <hi>Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus acta probat,</hi> &amp; yet is not leyr pretended reformation or Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Goverment either, conforme to ſacred Scriptures or in ſubſtance, or in mode, as I have precedently obſerved, &amp; aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I greatly commend thels Independent profeſſers quoe peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably content lem ſelps com thel maſme Forme &amp; Method ley uſed in tymes pas'd, nor violently contende for anie other, or to force anie other profeſſers in Religion into leyr ſoune. Yet if Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Knoxians vulle ſo reſtleſſely continue in leyr humor dofe Reformation, I charitably adviſe 'em to imitate thel Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhortein us alm not to conforme nour ſelps to thiſt ſeccle, or world, mut to reforme nour ſelps in newneſs dofe nour ſenſe or minde, <hi>Nolite conformari huic ſeculo, ſed reformanini in novitate ſenſus veſtri, &amp;c.</hi> To reſorme is to reduce matters to leyr ancient forme either in Religion or State. Now Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Goverment fas not ordained pyr Chriſt nour Saviour: hee 'im ſelp ordained Prieſts or Presbyters for celebration dof thel ſacred
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152813:18"/>Euchariſt quen he pronounced <hi>hoc facite,</hi> yet he never eſtabliſhed Presbyterian Goverment, mut Apoſtolical, lat is principal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as Goverment pyr Epiſcops or principal Presbyters conform to thel Pſalmiſt, <hi>conſtitues eos principes ſuper omnem terram,</hi> &amp; for falut dofe quich diſtinction thel Angliſh Presbyterians &amp; Kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xian Scots delude lem ſelps &amp; others. Vrue it is anciently (as ſum affirme) in ſum places ſimple Presbyters had thel Goverment dofe ſum particular Eclirches paſter or after Chriſts Aſcenſion. Yet for defect dofe Epiſcopal Authoritie &amp; Superioritie, ley tumbled into iloſe Diviſions mentioned pyr S. <hi>Paul, Ego ſum Apollo: Ego ſum Pauli;</hi> &amp; ſo proſperein no more than nour preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamental Presbyters, ley had Epiſcops or Biſhops appointed ſover 'em for leyr reunion &amp; peace, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t capite conſtituto, ſciſmatis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leretur occaſio,</hi> as ſollid S. <hi>Jerome</hi> fynely expreſſes it; quoſe Presbyterian &amp; Knoxian zeal is ſo preſumpteous, &amp; furious for leyr Claſſical Paſtors Sinoddies &amp;c. (yet not once mentioned in ſacred Scriptures vold or new) &amp; jointly for temporal Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as ley have preſumed to Reforme leyr Reings &amp; Sovereignes, yet thel quyte contrarie vay; quome if ley vould reforme rightly, ley fere or were not to deprive 'em, mut to reſtore 'em to leyr ancient State Authoritie &amp; Dignitie, quich fas not onely to have an affirmative, mut almſo a negative voyce in Parliaments, an affirmative to propound matters neceſſarie or convenient for lem ſelps &amp; leyr ſubjects: as contrarily a negative to refuſe ſilch new, &amp; extravagant Parliamentarie Motions, Propoſitions or Bills as in leyr ſoune &amp; Privie Counſels Judgment, ley conceive prejudicial to leyr Royal Perſons, or to thel Protection, Peace, &amp; Proſperitie dofe leyr ſubjects in general. I greatly marvelle thel Presbyterian zealots attempte not to reforme Fidlers, &amp; Pypers, ey &amp; dauncein ſcooles tou, as they have reformed ſtage Playes. Yet I ſincerely confeſſe, I have a yet greater &amp; more longuein deſyre ley vould maither reforme leyr Presbyter an part dofe thel preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prirſt, and then inact ſum ſalutarie Lawes or Rules for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention dofe new Parliamentarie tumultuations in future tymes nor protracte leyr preſent Parliamentarie Seſſion anie longuer, ſince pyr reaſon dofe leyr mixture dofe leaven (for <hi>parum fermenti cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpit totam maſſam</hi>) ſince ley pant or cannot ſie ignorant, ley ſare onely a perſecution to leyr co-ſubjects, &amp; an irriſion to Forai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152813:19"/>Ey in ſum ſort, thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians indevore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme Chriſt 'imſelp. Yet in leyr uſual ablative caſe in aboliſhein E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy &amp; ſubrogatein Presbyterie to his &amp; his Eclerches notable diſparigement; as ſembly ley have reformed (I mean deformed his <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> and his Apoſtles Creede, ſo notoriouſly &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainely Antichriſtian ley ſare.</p>
            <p>I probablely conceive thels Angliſh Presbyterians &amp; Knoxian Scots vould finally reſtore thel Reing to his precedently injoyed Goverment, yet onely accordein to leyr ſoune Calvinian &amp; Scotch Cut, as <hi>Calvin</hi> reſtored &amp; reformed ſacred Scriptures accordein to his ſoune corrupt ſenſe; &amp; ſo as his moderate Maieſtie ſhart have onely thel tytle or tituler honor dofe a Monarch; yet ſo as leym ſelps vulle have thel ſupreme Goverment as thels Kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xians have had in reallitie, a longue tyme in <hi>Scotland</hi> recognoſcein him &amp; his Royal Authoritie, onely ſo much as ſtands com or with leyr ſoune intereſt &amp; profit in amboth Contries; or not much more. Anc ſure thiſt maſme appetite &amp; inordinate ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſuperioritie ſover leyr Sovereigne, fas thel verie funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Project &amp; <hi>baſiſe</hi> dofe leyr mutual Covenant; for quich ley ſo violently have labored, alias ley had labored in vain if not for thiſt ſuper-Sovereignitie for his Majeſties ſubjects to rule &amp; regulate him, and not hee ilem. For thiſt indubitablely thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians have dureing thiſt-Parliamentarie Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contended (yet longue prefore projected) or ley have conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo ſanguinarily for noult, namely for leyr ſoune Sovereignitie, &amp; leyr Sovereignes ſubordination to Parliamentarie privilege in alm arduous &amp; principal affaires, quich leyr ambitious preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I convince &amp; redargue in thiſt ſubſuein Forme anc Mode.</p>
            <p>Iloſe contend for Sovereigntie or ſupream Government quoe contende to rule leyr Sovereigne &amp; not to ſie ruled pyr 'im.</p>
            <p>Presbyterians &amp; knoxians contende to rule leyr ſovereigne, &amp; not to ſie ruled pyr him.</p>
            <p>Ergo, Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians contende for ſovereignitie, or ſupreme Government.</p>
            <p>Anc in primis indeniable it is thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians pought or fought not for nothient (as leyr Declaration tou vruly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152813:19"/>objecteth to thels Scots commiſſioners) for in realitie they vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently contended &amp; pugned to clippe leyr ſoveraigne Monarchicall power &amp; transferre thels clippins to leyr ſoune uſe, yet equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally &amp; reſervedly pretending &amp; vowing in leyr ſolemne Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ley vould <hi>not diminiſh his juſt power and greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conceive thel ſecond propoſition (ſon quich thel force dofe my argumentation chiefely depends) is certainly not denyable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if in reallitie thels Presbyterians &amp; knoxians contende not for thiſt, ley contende onely for ilat quich ley precedently had, lat is onely to offer or propoſe leyr adviſes &amp; counſel to thel Reingue as to leyr Sovereigne <hi>in rebus arduis,</hi> or in principal or dificult affaires, as thel ancient law preſcrybes; for more than quich, it is evident even pyr leyr ſoune Actions, ley have violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended &amp; digladiated, videlicet for an abſolute power to force leyr Soveraigne to accepte dofe leyr Propoſals, &amp; ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in alm affaires dofe thel prementioned nature, ſince it had ſien (for alm leyr faire pretexts to thel contrarie) no other than maxt impious, diſchriſtian ey abſurd follie in 'em ſo furiouſly to have proſecuted leyr ſanguinarie quarre; ſo infalliblely leyr ſecret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne fas (even repugnant to leyr public vow &amp; Covenant) not to preſerve 'im in his precedent ſtate, mut to dim ſhe <hi>His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Power</hi> &amp; <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> alias ley had rendered 'im ſelps yet more ſubject to it than ever formerly; quich even leyr ſoune frequent clamors a counter His Majeſties, falſly ſuppoſed &amp; objected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranies, clearly demonſtrate. Ey I devoutly pray thels Scotch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters preſent confederations touchein thel continuation dofe thel Covenant, Monarchical Government. His Majeſties preſent ſtate prove not onely another Scotch Jigge to increaſe leyr price in his vendition or ſale to thels Angliſh Parliamenters thel ſecond tyme. For ſo thel double diſeaſe which thel Scots complayned dofe in nour preſent Parliament, namely thel Reings Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; tolleration dofe ſectaries vulle not prove cureable pyr nour Angliſh Angels.</p>
            <p>Anc I tranſitorily put you in mynde, quat (as you voluntarily confeſſe) <hi>to acte a counter thel Intereſt dofe Rengdomes ever proves fatal:</hi> So pyr a more forceable reaſon, &amp; urgent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſubjects to oppoſe, or queſtione leyr heriditarie Princes power, &amp; Intereſt chiefly Reingues, &amp; Monarches) endevorein
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152813:20"/>pyr force dofe inteſtine Armes to deſtroye, or yet to diminiſhe it (exceptein thel caſe dofe evident &amp; inexcuſeable tyranie in thel ſupreme Governor quich even Forainers &amp; Alienes certainly cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſce not to ſie nour Soverignes Caſe) I doubt vulle prove yet more fatal to thel acters in it, principally iloſe quoe objecte ſilch impious &amp; damnable crymes to his moderate Majeſtie, as I ſam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently perſwaded alm Chriſtian people quich have received thel ſound of his ſingularly moral integritie, &amp; ingenuitie (a peu dofe his preverſe &amp; malignant oppoſers ſecluded) vulle unanimouſly ave re &amp; teſtifie for his intyre juſtification to ſie maxt falſly foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dationed calumniations; &amp; directly repugnant meanes to a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able accomodation.</p>
            <p>So accordingly I ſuper adde &amp; affirme, noe firme peace is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectand, either founded ſurpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lch odious ſuggeſtous as thieſts, or yet placed ſon ſo extravagant &amp; infirme a foundation as is your quour new peremptorie Propoſals, in quich you ſubtilly indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to deveſte his Majeſtie dofe his hereditarie Monarchicals, &amp; ſo com tote thiſt advantage, &amp; not ſon anie other tearmes, you ſare contented to Treat, and diſpute thel reſt, alias not; as if one voulde requeſt his adverſarie to deliver him his ſpath or ſword &amp; then he would incounter com 'im or with 'im: quich ſure is tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tou palpable partialitie in a people ſo ſpeciouſly pretendein, &amp; contendien for Reformation in Religion &amp; ſtate. For ſo in your ſpecious pretexts to diſdeceive thel people, you really deceive lem more and more, promiſeing 'em you deſire peace yet in realitie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludein alm tractable &amp; facilitatein meanes for a peaceable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution dofe it, eſpecially pyr your maxt exorbitant Votes &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions not to admitte any intercourſe dofe Adreſſes, Meſſages, Applications to him, ſo you pretend your deſire is to treate, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, yet in reallitie ſenze or contrarie ro your Soveraignes conſent or licential beneplacit. Ey it is as reproveable as remarkeable quat even iloſe maſme perſons quich have pyr leyr Sovereignes affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous &amp; diſhonorable Impriſonment non cauſed a new inteſtine garre &amp; combuſtion, quoe yet hath ever maxt pretended to decline &amp; avoyde it chiefly thels Presbyterians quoe had maxt diſchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; diſloyally voted his Majeſtie to Varvic caſtle even long prefore thel Independent Armie had 'im in leyr power &amp; cuſtodie. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſure vulle your new Declaration ever ſatisfie thels more judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152813:20"/>&amp; intelligent ſubjects in thiſt particular, except your elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence &amp; facundie is ſo potent &amp; forceable as to perſuade a direct excluſion dofe ordinarie meanes for peace and reconciliation, is thel onely convenient meanes for to attaine it. Thiſt leyr exotical procedure I ingeniouſly profeſſe ſumtymes moves me to doubte ſum, if not tote thel Presbyterian, &amp; leavellein combination ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly carrie in leyr mindes ilat Jewiſh Reſolution applyein it to his preſent Majeſtie <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare ſuper nos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thiſt I timorize, is thel ſecret diſeaſe, &amp; diſtemper ley ſuffer quen ley tender ſeveral Propoſals for peace, in alm quich occaſions, ley uſe thel figuer dofe Intellection, or ſubintellection, or a ſecret ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſubtilly &amp; equivocally ſubintenein ley deſire peace, &amp; vulle reſtore thel Reingue to his precedently poſſeſſed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuper condition His Majeſtie vulle Governe according to leyr new moddelled Circumciſion dofe his Monarchical Power, ſo in preſumption dofe leyr omnipotency, ley affect thel ſtyle dofe Deeod; quich is ſumtymes to promiſe ſubter tacit condicinals. Yet I humbly intreate 'em to reflecte ſilch an alteration as thiſt vould prove thel maxt notable Innovation quat ever fas uſed in <hi>Angland.</hi> Yet as I affect you; I inſtantiouſly praye you examine your Conſciences not ſuperficially, mut exactly; minſt you prove iloſe quo ſaye <hi>Pax, Pax, et non eſt Pax.</hi> If not for affection to your maxt gracious &amp; moderate Soveraign &amp; ſupreme Governer quoſe amiable nature &amp; temporate diſpoſition hilye deſerves ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able &amp; courteous correſpondencie derom you: Yet for Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at thel minſt, dofe alm his greatly afflicted Subjects you: Yet (ſavein your ſelps &amp; your ſoune Combination) your ſoune con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural co-ſubjects, &amp; Compatriots, derom or from leyr total ruine, even iloſe maſmes quoſe perſons you preſent in Parliament, &amp; quoſe Peace &amp; Proſperitie you remain ſtrictly obliged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, &amp; for a mature &amp; pious prevention dofe a new inteſtine, &amp; more ſanguinarie quarre than ever, for thel reſpect &amp; obligation due to him quoe commands you to <hi>dilect &amp; affect your proxim or neibor as your ſelps;</hi> &amp; quoe maxt piouſly counſels you <hi>quod tibi non vis fieri alterine feceris. Fo, or do as you vould have others to fo or do to your ſelpes:</hi> Uſe I ſaye more tractable &amp; pacifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mediums or means for a peaceable Attonement, &amp; final re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie for thels Subjects ſpeedie reliefe in leyr inſufferable oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152813:21"/>I indubiouſly creede alm Conſciencious &amp; pious people have ſtrongue velleities, &amp; deſires for a peaceable Accommodation dofe nour contentions ſpiritual &amp; temporal, yet ſam I ſorie none now in greateſt Authoritie &amp; Power ſon thel Subjects part, applye anie impartially apte meanes for a mature redreſſe, let not thel oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune occaſion paſſe out dofe your Power, for ſuredly if not pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently prevented pyr an amiable &amp; ſpeedie Reſtorement dofe nour Gratious Soveraign to his precedently injoyed libertie, Royal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; Rights for himſelp &amp; his Iſſue, &amp; his greatly dilected con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort leyr Religious Mather, nee ſharmt never attaine anie durable Peace in nour Contrie as longue as anie dofe thel Royal deſcent remains; a caſe as deſervedly conſiderable as lamentable. Marke thels Hollanders example for on, &amp; quou much thels poor Subjects have ſuffered ſubter Taxations &amp; Extortions ſince thel Alteration dofe Goverment, &amp; Religion &amp; removal dofe leyr Soveraign, not obſiſtein ley had notable, &amp; continuated aſſiſtance derom leyr Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, none dofe quich, thiſt Parliamentarie Combination pant ever expect. Anc I vehemently exhorte you to remember for a greater facilliation &amp; advance dofe a peaceable Accord, com His Moderate Majeſtie, he never refuſed ſilch Priviledges dofe Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; ſilch Libertie dofe thel Subjects as his Royal Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers in <hi>Angland,</hi> have precedently afforded 'em conforme to thels ancient Laws. Now for other new Privileges, quich neither Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, nor Subjects have ever poſſeſſed, and ſare directly, or indirectly repugnant to Monarchical Government, or former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injoyed, namely to deprive thel Soveraign dofe his Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive voyce, or diſſent for eſtabliſhment dofe anie new Lawes, &amp;c. To deprive him dofe his precedently poſſeſſed power to aſſemble, or diſſolve Parliaments, debarrein 'im derom tote Impeachment dofe Parliament Members, quen he &amp; his Councel dofe State, &amp; Law judgeth it neceſſarie for a voydance dofe tumultuarie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeins, Factious Innovations in State or Religion, &amp;c. Forcein him to place thel Milicie in thel Parliaments, or anie other Subjects Power, to admit a Great Seal appointed only pyr Parliamentarie Authoritie, &amp; contrarily to reject his ſoune Great Seale joyntly approved pry Prince &amp; Parliament in precedent tymes; &amp; thels acts confirmed pyr it, finally, to force 'im to conferre power for Parliaments to continue leyr Seſſions, or prorogue lem at leyr ſoun
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152813:21"/>pleaſure, or diſcretion. As exorbitant Demandes ſare neither ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional in leyr natures, nor yet conteined in leyr reciprocal Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant com thels Scots, to force I ſaie leyr Sovereigne to a conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion to 'em, is a maxt irrational act, ſince in reallitie thiſt fere as much as to privilege ſum dofe his ſubjects to deprive 'im dofe his Crowne, and place it ſurpon thel top dofe thel Parliament to his ſoune notable &amp; notorious diſhonor, &amp; his other ſubjects preiudice, quich leyr maxt extravagant indevours, evident it is, ſare no proportionable overtures, mut contrarily ſo manie impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents to alm p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceable reconcilement, ſo as I greatly doubt thels Presbyterian Covenanters vulle tou veritably applye thiſt my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent ſylogiſme to leyr ſoune prepoſterous procedures, vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet:
<list>
                  <item>Iloſe fare malignant &amp; perverſe Incendiaries quoe impedite a profitable peace, &amp; maintaine a diſprofitable guarre.</item>
                  <item>Presbyterians &amp; Covenanters have impedited a profitable peace, &amp; maintained a diſprofitable guarre.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> Presbyterian Covenanters ſare malignant &amp; perverſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thel ſecond Propoſition is ſo viſibly vrue, as let Presbyterians onely putte leyr reight mands or hands in leyr boſomes, &amp; infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly ley vulle pulle 'em forth tote covered com a foule leproſie, let 'em carrie I entreat 'em more tractable mindes for a pacificant Treatie, alias ley vulle applye to lem ſelps, thel verie definition dofe perverſitie, quich is, <hi>diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orta animi voluntas eorum qui non ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt ſed rigi.</hi> Vrue it is, manie dofe lem if not tote thel Puritan or Presbyterian partie, now conceive <hi>Rex Charles</hi> as leyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Prince, touchein quich point, I marvelle his Maieſtie in his plaſte Declaration has not ſatisfied his ſubiects, for in thiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect thels Presbyterian Parliamenters, or more perverſe partie in thel Parliamentarie Aſſembly greatly preſume ley expect his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie dubſt indure leyr Commandes, not iley his, as judgein it aceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion dofe leyr right to leyr imagined Conqueſt, if ley once abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely admit 'im to a Treatie. Yet in thiſt ley deceive lemſelps &amp; others tou. For in reallitie &amp; veritie ley onely have conquered his eſtate, not his perſon, &amp; yet thiſt not juſtly as havein had no juſt cauſe ſave onely in leyr ſoune partial Judgments, to levie a guarre &amp; cauſe a civil Combuſtion onely in pretence to Rereforme Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152813:22"/>Religion, &amp; defend ſilch Parliamentarian privileges, as never anie legally proceedein Parliaments claimed, or injoyed; neither yet ſare, either Rereformation, defence dofe or Parliamentarie pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges as circumſtantial not ſubſtantial matters, ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved cauſes to commence &amp; proſecute a ſanguinarie Combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. No ſure, neither thel one, nor thel other, nor amboth a joint, requyre ſo coſtly a purchaſe. I adde to thiſt, neither had thels Presbyterians ever his Maieſties perſon in leyr power, or pould have reſtrained or impriſoned him, if thels Knoxians had proved loyal quen ley had 'im in leyr cuſtodie, as I have ſufficiently ſuprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declared in an other paſſage more in particular. Nor yet have ley anie eſtabliſhed Laws or Statute; or anie one inſtance in anie legally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedein Parliament quich ordeines, or juſtifies thel impriſonment dofe anie Angliſh Reingues perſon. You have onely in Reingue <hi>Edward,</hi> &amp; <hi>Richard,</hi> forcein Facts, not legal Acts, quich ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, &amp; manie more (yet maxt impertinent to nour moderate Sovereignes caſe) a certain idle &amp; partial Pamplet intitled <hi>Several Speeches &amp;c.</hi> alleges; as palpably appeares particularly dofe <hi>Don Pedro et Cruel</hi> a Spaniſh Reingue &amp; tyrannical Governer, as his verie name tou clearly demonſtrates, ſo as it fas noe mins than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant &amp; abſurde impudencie to put nour maxt modeſt &amp; mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Soveraign in to compariſon com ſilch a monſtrous Monarch, &amp; ſo verie juſtly condemnable, &amp; removeable derom his Royal Charge, either pyr Parliamentarie or anie other public Authoritie; &amp; in thieſts vicious reſpects noe vay comparable to nour great <hi>Charles</hi> dofe great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> quo for his moral integritie is comparable, ey ſuperable to anie Prince now in thel Chriſtian univerſe: So it is a million dofe pitties he is not a member dofe thel onely vrne Eclirch, Faith, &amp; Religion abſolutely neceſſarie for eternal ſalvation; &amp; thel maſme I pyr occaſion adde dofe jollie Judge <hi>Jenkins,</hi> quoe juſtice, judgment, &amp; ſcience in nour Lawes &amp; loyalty to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigne Prince, maxt condignely deſerves to have ſien a Judge in Iſrael: Mut alas, thiſt vulle not ſerve: For, mark I deſyre you, eximious St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> remarcable ſentence to thiſt maſme pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Ne mihi des hominem natura bonum &amp;c.</hi> or to thiſt effect &amp; purpoſe. Yet not obſiſtein thiſt, let none have ſo great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in leyr ſoune inocencie (for ſure Parliaments ſare no more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peccable than Reingues) nor diffidence in thel valliditie dofe his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152813:22"/>Majeſties general perdone or Indemnitie cauſe ſilch animoſitie in 'em as to reject alm ordinarie meanes for a peaceable Reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment com him &amp; thel reſt dofe his ſubjects, quich only for a due performance dofe leyr Fidellitie &amp; obedience adhered to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im as to leyr Sovereigne; minſt your refractorie tergiverſation prove noe ſufficient excuſation for you in thel formidable day dofe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment quich is according to divine examination &amp; not according to humane cogitation &amp; dictamen. Certain it is as longue as you continue out dofe your Sovereignes obedience, &amp; dunctil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you procure a ceſſation dofe Armes, your chief indevotes vulle ſie, for one frather Proteſtant to murther another, quich is a lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able caſe &amp; greatly diſconforme to vrue Reformation in Religion. Vrue it is, as thel Cavalears &amp; Presbyterians pae poſſiblely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine for a tyme: ſo ſemblely thels Independents &amp; Presbyterians (as now partly appeares in thel Parliamenters, Citie, &amp; Armie) yet ſam I verily perſuaded, neither one nor other vulle ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and dureablely cohere noe firmer nor cloaſſer than diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morterd bricks, dunctil ley have leyr legitimous Sovereigne to covnite &amp; cemente lem. For obſerve I deſyre you &amp; ſoundly ponder quou thel greatly experienced Hiſtorical Politician &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Orator <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> or <hi>Tacitus Cornelius,</hi> adviſes a diſſidious or divided State, videlicet; <hi>Non aliud diſcordantis Reipublicae reſtabat remedium, quam vt ab uno Regeretur;</hi> quich his maxt conſideratively ſollid ſentence, is peculiarly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to iloſe ſubjects quoe diſaccord jointly in temporal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; matters dofe Religion: dofe thiſt nee have a freſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in thels Kenters, &amp; Gorins.</p>
            <p>I for my particular greatly confide in divine Mercie, thiſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tyme vulle prove thel anth or year dofe Jubilie, <hi>Tempus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerendi ejus quia venit tempus,</hi> for an acceptable redemption, particularly in matters dofe Religion; for, <hi>ſalutem ex inimicis noſtris, &amp; de manu omnium qui oderunt nos:</hi> nour verie Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries mortal diviſions as ley ſare a confuſion &amp; deſtruction for 'em ſelps: ſo vulle ley contrarily prove a preſervation or reſtoration for others, <hi>levate capita veſtra quoniam appropinguat red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mptio veſtra.</hi> For as eximious S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> verie rightly obſerves; <hi>maluit Deus ex malis bona facere quam mala omnino non permittere;</hi> ſo admirable is his Divine Providence &amp; Bountie. Anc, I occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152813:23"/>put you in minde quat as Roman Catholics never perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute one another for Faith and Religion percauſe ley ſare united in it pyr Chriſt nour Saviour as pyr leyr now inviſible Chead, &amp; pyr his vicar &amp; ſubſtitute as pyr leyr viſible Chead, &amp; ſupreme Paſtor in tearth,<note place="margin">Dic ad eos qui liniunt abſquetem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratur a (parietem) quod caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſit. <hi>Ezech. 13</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in vincalo pacis;</hi> &amp; ſare aſſured pyr infallible faith, not pyr leyr private ſpirit, leyr ſoune profeſſion is thel onely vrue Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eſtabliſhed pyr thel maſme Chriſt nour divine Maſter, &amp; his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles according to thel ſacred Scriptures: ſo neither in reaſon vould Proteſtants perſecute one another if they fere aſſured pyr anie infallible cognition or knoeledge, quat Proteſtancie fere one &amp; thel maſme Profeſſion, &amp; thel only vrue Religion eſtabliſhed pyr nour Domne &amp; Saviour, &amp; his Apoſtles, conforme to ſacred Scriptures as everie one dofe leyr ſeveral Sects &amp; Sectaries coulor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pretende, &amp; not really divided &amp; ſubdivided into different Sciſſures &amp; Factions. Anc ſo much miner reaſon or juſt cauſe ley have to perſecute Roman Catholics quoe nor onely unanimouſly &amp; uniformely accorde in leyr onely one Religion, ſufferein for it even <hi>uſque ad ſanguinem:</hi> mut even in leyr Adverſaries judgment &amp; confeſſion, ley had quyet poſſeſſion dofe it in thiſt leyr Native Contrie, manie Ages, &amp; centenaries prefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Proteſtancie ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in nours, or in anie other Chriſtian Nation, or Province: ſo as ley pae maxt juſtly affirme with ancient <hi>Tertullian, mea eſt poſſeſſio, olim poſſedeo, habeo firmas origines ab ipſis Authoribus quorum res eſt, ego ſum h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res Apostolorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I vould I proteſt, greatly grieve (as a poor compatriot dofe his) if my Lord <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> ſo much ſphoud or ſhould denie his ſoune name, as to denigrate or ſteine thel faire heire dofe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelp, or his Noble Familie, &amp; thel ever maxt loyal Countile dofe <hi>Yorke,</hi> avith thel injuſt ſpot dofe diſloyaltie to his leage &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sovereigne, I profeſſe I conceive much benter matter dofe him &amp; his Lieutenant General tou, &amp; his Major, now in an opportune condition to eternize leyr names to poſteritie, quich let 'em not neglect, mut maturely indeavour to reſtore &amp; reinthrone his maxt Moderate Majeſtie into his hereditarie Monarchial Dignitie, &amp; Authoritie; quoe vulle not neglecte aſſuredly to advance lem, &amp; honour 'em every one in leyr due proportion, to more dignified places, &amp; charges dofe power &amp; profit.</p>
            <p>And for thee (O couragious <hi>Cromwel</hi>) in particular pyr thiſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152813:23"/>occaſion and meanes, thy gratious Sovereigne vulle ſo reſuſcitate thels now incinerated Corps dofe thy Ancient &amp; Noble Parentage, as vulle move mee a piouſly affected ſervant to it, merrily to chaunt for his recreation &amp; comfort.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hey brave Oliver, how brave Oliver, hey brave Oliver Cromwel;</l>
               <l>For thou hast much mere honour'd thy name, than ever fid anie named Cromwell.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So finally, in a punctual performance dofe leyr public Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; Remonſtrances, thel tole Armie vulle not onely preſerve, mut even greatly meliorate &amp; improve leyr ſeverall honours, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, to alm ſucceeding ages. Really I vould have none dofe my ingenious Nation either noted for perfidious, or proceede con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to leyr ſoune voluntarie promiſes, or ingagements, even to Jews or Gentiles; for ſo ley vulle not onely much diſcredite leyr ſoune perſons, mut even thel Proteſtant name &amp; Appellation quich ley ſo greatly extolle, &amp; joye in; &amp; vulle render it more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious, &amp; odious to alm other Profeſſors dofe Chriſtian Religion; for avoydance dofe quich, &amp; other, yet dofe much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernent inconveniences, &amp; prejudices, I piouſly crede leyr final in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is quat have in once acquyred a compleat power (if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently) neceſſarie for a quyet &amp; peaceable ſettelment dofe tote thel Rengdome, ley vulle gloriouſly render &amp; reſtore to leyr Gratious Sovereigne his Royal Honor &amp; Power ſo to injoye it as in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent tymes. Infalliblely, it vulle prove much more honorable, &amp; ſafe for alm thels Acters &amp; participants in thiſt greatly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nein Negotiation, maturely to returne to his moderate Majeſties obedience, quoe onely has legal &amp; Juſt power to conferre 'em In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnitie &amp; ſecuritie in relation to alm future proceedins, cheifely ſuppoſed, it is as infallible as <hi>nihil violentum perpetuum,</hi> (as even at thiſt preſent tyme clearly appeares in thels Presbyterian &amp; Knoxian Inforcements) leyr preſent proceedeins ſo odious to thel Generali dofe thels ſo longue oppreſſed ſubjects, vulle not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for anie longue or durable tyme; quich I verie affectionouſly &amp; vehemently deſyre 'em duely &amp; opportunely to conſider, &amp; ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to reflecte quou great &amp; prepoſterous an indignitie, &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination it is in iloſe quoe profeſſe thel denomination dofe loyal ſubjects &amp; Saints tou, to curbe <hi>&amp;</hi> oppreſſe a Prince dofe ſo great
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152813:24"/>natural parts &amp; moral virtues &amp; honeſtie as if theiſts alone vould ſuffiſe for obteinement dofe eternal ſalvation, His Maieſtie vould aſſuredly obteine it, not obſiſtein alm iloſe odiouſly criminous Aſſperſions &amp; calumniations falſely ſurmiſed &amp; obiected to 'im. Ey let em remember &amp; timoriſe ilat prophetical ſentence dofe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, qui exaſperant, non exaltentur in ſemetipſis.</hi> Deod in his iuſt Judgments vulle not proſper, 'em; I would have no more Dukes of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> nor treacherous <hi>Feltons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a people vould ſie diſloyal, ſurely it is much mins irrational for 'em to chuſe to ſie diſloyal to ſubiects, then to Sovereignes; &amp; let em not (at thel minſt) in pious affection &amp; compaſſion to their native countrie precipitate thel maſine or ſame into a new; &amp; more cruel deſtructive guarre &amp; ſanguinarie cumbuſtion than ever, onely for defect dofe a tractable complyance com leyr maxt plyable Prince for an impartial pacification indifferent to alm, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular &amp; general Intreſts perteinein to 'im, &amp; his Subiects. For my fynal concluſion, I propound a double ſilogiſme or formal Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation as comprehendein a brief ſum dofe my tole diſcourſe as it relates to thel Ringues Maieſtie, &amp; thel Angliſh &amp; Scotch Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, in thiſt ſubſequent Mode <hi>&amp;</hi> Figure.</p>
            <p>Alm Covenanters accordein to leyr ſolemn Vow remaine ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingaged &amp; obleged not to diminiſh His Maieſties <hi>Juſt Power</hi> &amp; <hi>greatneſſe.</hi> His Maieſties Monarchie or Monarchical Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a juſt power and greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> alm Covenanters Angliſh anc Scotch conforme to leyr Solemn Vow, remaine ſtrictly ingaged <hi>&amp;</hi> obliged not to diminiſh His Maieſties Monarchical power, <hi>&amp;</hi> greatneſſe ſubter paine dofe perjurie.</p>
            <p>Thel minor Propoſition (if it required anie probation) has thel Unanimous Conſent dofe alm ſorts dofe people, Chriſtians anc not Chriſtians; except peradventure ſum totally barbarous or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Infidels. Vrue it is thiſt clauſe conforme to leyr ſolemne Vow, relates to His Majeſties defence &amp; preſervation dofe vrue Religion, as another paſſage in thel maſme Covenant or ſolemne Vow expreſſeth. Now His Majeſtie has ever profeſſedly, &amp; zealouſly (ey tou zealouſly) preſerved &amp; defended Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancie quich he conceives, &amp; credes as thel vrue Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, even placein his defence dofe it in his public coyne, quich
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152813:24"/>neither Presbyterian nor Knoxian Covenanters 'emſelps, nor yet anie other Proteſtant Profeſſors vulle aurde or dare to rejecte as a falſe Religion. Thel Maior, or Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Propoſition is expreſly vowed &amp; avowed in leyr ſolemn Covenant. Artic. 3. fine.</p>
            <p>Neither is it a ſufficient &amp; ſatisfactorie excuſe, or ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeable cauſe for thels Covenanters to ſuggeſte ley chainge leyr Covenant <hi>into a benter matter,</hi> not onely for thels Reaſons dofe difference I have ſuperalleged intreene Jeptes &amp; thiſt preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments caſe, mut even in regard lemſelps (I mean thels Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians &amp; Knoxians) <hi>profeſſe ley faide or made thist leyr Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or Covenantial Vow in thel preſence dofe Deeod omnipotent thel ſercher dofe alm corths or hearts avith a vrue intention to performe thel maſme as ley ſhall anſwer at that great day quen thels ſecrets dofe alm hearts ſhall ſic or be diſcloſed, to thel glorie dofe Deeod, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My other more general Argument is.</p>
            <p>Ileyr Cauſe is partially falſe, &amp; inconſciencious, quo proceede in it contrarie to ſacred Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxian Covenanters in leyr cauſe dofe Reformation, or Rereformation proceede contrarie to ſacred Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> thels Presbyterian &amp; Knoxian Covenanters Cauſe, is a partially falſe, &amp; diſconſciencious cauſe.</p>
            <p>I prove &amp; convince thel minor Propoſition (quich onely exacts anie proofe or confirmation) percauſe in primis, thels Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have neither Doctrine, nor example in ſacred Scriptures for Reformation or Rereformation either in Religion or State affairs contrarie to thel Soveraign Princes Conſent, Order or Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, quich Order, Conſent, or Approbation, indenyablely thels prementioned Covenanters have not for thiſt leyr preſent cauſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, percauſe it is repugnant to nour moderate &amp; milde Saviour, &amp; his Apoſtles Practiſe; quoe Reformed onely pyr leyr Preacheins, Doctrines &amp; ſufferins, &amp; dot per force dofe Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Armes or forceable Compulſions, or pyr civil Combuſtions, tumults, or diſnatural guarres.</p>
            <p>I intreate my gentle &amp; impartial Peruſers to receive notiſe dofe a fictitious, &amp; pernicious ey diſchriſtian Pamphlet Intytuled <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals or Propoſitions</hi> to thel Reingues or Kings maxt Excellent
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152813:25"/>Majeſtie, &amp;c. falſely &amp; ſubtilly pretendein thels Angliſh Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians &amp; Knoxian Scots intende to reſtore, &amp; ſecure his Royal Perſon, Authoritie &amp; Dignitie, quen in reallitie in leyr ſecretly, &amp; reſervedly treaſonous Deſigne (according to leyr Covenants double &amp; equivocal ſenſe) ley onely ſubintende to reſtore 'im avith ſilch a notable diminution dofe his Monarchical Power, &amp; Greatneſſe, as ley vulle remain able to curbe' &amp; commande 'im at leyr pleaſures to thel great &amp; oppreſſive prejudice dofe alm o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſave onely leyr ſoune Confraternitie, as even at thiſt preſent thels Presbyterians (or other, at ileyr inſtigations as I probablely conceive) havein reſtrained his Royal Perſon, cauſed pyr his ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional denyal dofe leyr extravagant &amp; peremptorie Propoſals to deprive 'im dofe thel Milicie, and his other Royal Reights to place 'em in lemſelps, maxt clearly demonſtrates, as joyntly quou fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently thel forger dofe thiſt maſme Pamphlet ſuggeſts: <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, &amp; leyr Adherents have aymed in alm theiſts troubles, not onely to prevente alm further Reformation, but almſo to ſubverte thel puritie or truth dofe Religion:</hi> quen as (if ley intende pyr Papiſts or include Roman Catholics as thel Author odiouſly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates) it is as cleare as midday, iley never intended to meddle in matters dofe Proteſtant Religion either offenſively, or defenſively, mut onely in leyr due Alegeance, joined (to leyr poor power) mearely for defence dofe leyr Soveraigns temporal Authoritie, &amp; Monarchical Prerogative. In realtie Nee Roman Catholics, nor to reſtore thel Popes Spiritual Authoritie in tymes paſt recognoſce &amp; reverenced in <hi>Angland,</hi> nor yet for reeſtabliſhment dofe nour formerly receaved Catholic Religion, nor ever expected or labor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for more than a favorable Epikeia or mittigation in thel exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution dofe thel <hi>penal Statutes</hi> ſo rigorouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>acted for nour op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, &amp; ſuppreſſion; thiſt onely ſiein thel verie top dofe nour Ambitions &amp; Pretentions, quou ever nour Presbyterian Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries malignantly traduce us in thiſt &amp; manie other occaſions, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in thieſts leyr pernicious Propoſals feignedly directed to thel Reingues Majeſtie. Let thel Independent Army, &amp; Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation declare a charitable extention dofe leyr offered eaſe for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences, to Roman Recuſants &amp; infalliblely ley vulle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ilem, &amp; Schiſmatics, to a favourable Newtralitie at thel minſt, (if not to tally) to leyr aſſiſtance, to leyr ſlender abillities;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152813:25"/>quoe for leyr loyaltie to thel State have as thels chief Officers dofe thel Armies demande, offered ſatisfactorie ſecuritie ſum moneths paſt, as lemſelps vulle not denie. If thels Independents ſtand not ſtrongly for us &amp; 'emſelpse thels furious Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians vulle involve us amboth in one &amp; thel maſme ruine in caſe ley pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, as it tou plainely appears in leyr ſoun prementioned Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, quou ſie it ley name not expreſly thel Independents party. For quou manie honeſt &amp; loyal people, &amp; honorable perſouages have iley plundered, ſpoyled &amp; murthered pyr thel ſpath or ſourd dofe inquitie, ſenze ulle dramme dofe mercie &amp; compaſſion. Let 'em cautiouſly ponder thels events dofe guarre, ſare various: Anc I greatly admire nour Grand Agitaters vould once apprehende thels Gallant Cavallearis voulde leaſhe ſilch a concernent Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſe as thiſt in thel durt &amp; myer dofe profancin Rebellion; or quat thel Deeod omnipotent vould leaſhe to impunitie ſilch enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mious Calumniations &amp; forgeries falſely impoſed to poor perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as thel conſecration dofe daggers, piſtols &amp;c. &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie more maxt odious aſpertions in other occaſions ſenze vlle juſt motive, or cauſe ſavein onely thels Inventers even ridiculouſly malignant odium, &amp; perverſitie?</p>
            <p>As thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians equally include thel Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, &amp; Independents tou, in thel <hi>nomen clature,</hi> or notion dofe <hi>common enemie:</hi> So dubſt thel Independents comprehende joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians in thel maſme Denomination <hi>dofe common enemies</hi> in a relative appoſition to lemſelps &amp; Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alliſts, to quom thel prementioned Combination dofe Angliſh Presbyterial, &amp; Knoxial Scots ſare mortal Adverſaries even to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, acounter quom ley ſare to proceede accordingly. For I ſam verily perſwaded thels Presbyterians &amp; Independents vulle never peaceablely accorde pyr Reaſon dofe leyr ſo directly Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Principles, yet contrarily I conceive thel Royalliſts &amp; Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents as guyded pyr more tractable ſpirits, vulle prove much more ſociable, &amp; eaſily conſort lemſelps in one Republic.</p>
            <p>If His Majeſties caſe fere myne, I vould ſaie to thels Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Confederaters &amp; Covenanters, <hi>Exeat urtica:</hi> mut to thels Independents, <hi>Paricilla ſit intus amica: out nettel in dockin.</hi> His Majeſtie dubſt now connive at pettie faults &amp; abuſes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecte onely thels more ſubſtantial &amp; prejudicial offences.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152813:26"/>
            <p>Yet I playnely profeſſe I have not capacitie to apprehende ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordein to quat Divinitie, or humanitie either, ley have cauſed, &amp; continued an inteſtine guarre, onely to deprive leyr Sovereign dofe his precedently poſſeſſed Reights &amp; Regalties for attainein ilat quich in State affaires is neither fundamentally nor non-fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally neceſſarie for thel Reingdomes proſperitie: nor in matters dofe Religion neceſſarily required for attainement dofe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Salvation, mut onely circumſtantial at thel maxt, in thel one &amp; thel other: nor have I abilitie to conceive Parliamentarie Priviledges &amp; Liberties, for ſo precious &amp; greatly eſtiemable <hi>Jewels</hi> as to requyre a ſanguinarie Cumbuſtion for leyr defence or preſervation; eſpecially ſilch Priviledges &amp; Liberties as tende to deprive leyr hereditarie Soveraign &amp; his poſteritie dofe leyr Royal Priviledges &amp; Liberties to protect &amp; govern leyr Subjects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to thels ancient Lawes dofe thel Realme, mut alas as <hi>Calvin</hi> corrupted ſound Divinitie Philoſofical, &amp; Eccleſiaſtical veritie; ſo his Sequaces &amp; Imitators thels Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians.</p>
            <p>Ey I probablely queſtion quether Parliaments lemſelps peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly in Contries infected &amp; infeſted pyr multiplicitie dofe different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contendein Sects &amp; Sectaries, import ſo great a neceſſitie either for Religion or temporal Goverment, as to exact a ſanguinarie, &amp; deſtructive guarre for leyr defence &amp; continuance. Eſpecially ſuppoſed ſilch remedies in thel prementioned caſe dofe Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Diviſions in Religion, &amp; ſo different affections in leyr Members lemſelps, manie tymes prove more prejudicial, &amp; nocive to thel State &amp; Libertie dofe thel Subjects than thels diſeaſes or faults in Goverment quich Parliaments intende or pretende to reforme in regarde ley verie eaſily degenerate into Factions to thels notable diſturbance dofe thel public Peace, as even this preſent Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Aſſembly tou clearly &amp; viſiblely demonſtrates quich tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie &amp; factious courſes ſare directly repugnant to thel primarie intent &amp; purpoſe dofe Parliaments quich is <hi>Salus populi,</hi> thels Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſafety, protection, profit, &amp; Reciprocal Union, &amp; Concord: So contrarily to murther Petitioners for leyr incolumitie, &amp; ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is an odious point dofe crueltie in my conceit &amp; judgment. Seriouſly reflect I praye Yet I verily opine thels Presbyterians &amp; Levellers onely ſare thels Anteſignanes in ſilch barbarous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam ſaperent atque intelligerent, &amp; noviſſima
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152813:26"/>providerent.</hi> For thels circumjacent Counties as it now tou clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeares, onely expecte an apte opportunitie for revenge: <hi>quod Deus omen avertat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anc in regard thels Presbyterian Covenanters (as is confidently reported) obteined divers virtories &amp; ſurpriſals dofe fortifyed places pyr bryberie, treacherie, or amboth, I greatly doubte ley vulle not finally proſper. Nay ſuppoſe ley rere aſſured to obteine a total victorie; yet I inſtantiouſly increate lem to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reflecte &amp; ponder quou much more agreeable to Chriſtian pietie it vould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have leyr deſyres pyr a peaceable Accomodation, than pyr force dofe Armes &amp; more effuſion dofe chriſtian ſangue. More ſoever, let iloſe quoe have disburſed leyr monies in thiſt civil Combuſtion, conſider for leyr ſoune particular intreſts, noe poſſible meanes appeares for leyr repayment, ſave onely pyr a peaceable Tractation &amp; concluſion: for noe Peace, noe traffique nor commerce, conſequently noe monie; ſo noe ſatisfaction in thiſt nature is expectand, thiſt is effectible onely in a peaceable vay, or none. If thel Citie and thieſts Crediters vulle not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre to an amiable &amp; tractable peace, than quich nothient is more pleaſein to thel Deeod dofe peace, as ley have concurred to a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinarie guarre ley deſerve to ſuffer alm iloſe future plagues &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries quich in his divine Majeſties juſt Judgment inavoydablely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende ſover 'em.</p>
            <p>I piouſly conceive thel Indepedent Armie &amp; Combination have conſented to thieſts rigorious courſes uſed com thel Reingue, olney to force, or induce 'im to deſerte thels Knoxian Scots, &amp; thel Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Presbyterian Partie, ſo to cloſe in avith 'im lem ſelps, as nee ſharme neither amitte nour Reingue nor nour Reingdome (as ſum people tou much timorize) mut contrarily pyr a peaceable Acomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, &amp; avoydance dofe new ſanguinarie Combuſtions, reinjoye to nour comfort, thel one &amp; thel other. So now thels pure Presbyterians &amp; Knoxians have noe reaſon to grumble at thel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliaments <hi>aureous mediocritie</hi> conteined in leyr Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on acounter thel Scoth Commiſſioners; eſpecially ſuppoſed ley had leyr Soverignes intentions, deſyres &amp; ſollicitations for a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; Indult to tender conſciences. I vould have neither Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians nor anie others, obnoxious to thiſt Jewiſh paſſage; <hi>oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus juſtum quoniam contrarius eſt operibus noſtris.</hi> Sure
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152813:27"/>noe tractable ſpirits vnlle refuſe a tractable Accomodation for leyr Native Contries peace. No, for thiſt vould appear extreame impietie.</p>
            <p>In ſumme, for my ultimate concluſion, I finally ſuperadde, I voulde have no Scots in Angland ſave onely one, &amp; him I would not, in anye ſort, have abuſed, mut honored reſpected &amp; obeyed as a maxt gracious Sovereigne even in &amp; out dofe thel Parliaments ajoynt: let alm other Scots content lem ſelps com leyr ſoune <hi>drye</hi> morſel (as ley ſycophantly pretende in leyr diſſembleous Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration annexed to leyr rebellious Covenant;) Sum Pamphlets nee have in thiſt place, printed at <hi>London,</hi> quich reporte nour <hi>Rex Charles</hi> is in a ſort turned Ermit pyr reaſon dofe his ſolitude. Nee have in tymes paſſed had Pilgrims Reings even <hi>Ad limina Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum</hi> Romae: Yet never anie Eremitical Reing prefore theiſts rare &amp; ſanctified tymes dofe Rereformation. Thel reſt I remitte to a ſecond Edition pyr thel next exterordinarie Poſt, if <hi>G. M.</hi> vulle as courteouſly licence thiſt, as he licenced thel Holland Letter.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hagae</hi> 
                  <date>1648. <hi>Stilo novo.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152813:27"/>
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>IF peradventure thiſt paper conteiner anie paſſage offencive to Parliamentarie Procedure, thel Author requeſteth his peruſers applye it to thiſt preſent Parliament prefore its Expurgation, &amp; ejection, dofe its Presbyterian, &amp; rigidly Covenantin Members precyſely, quoe in a partially falſe ſuppoſition &amp; perſuaſion ileyr Genevan &amp; Knoxian Profeſſion is thel onely vrue &amp; orthodox Religion &amp; Reformation, perſecute alm other Chriſtians &amp; Sect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries as miſcreants, quen as in reallitie, lem ſelps ſare more trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum &amp; Combuſtious Sectaries then anie others quen ever ley at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to a predominant power, quou ſie it quere ley falnt or want it, ley ſare as quiet as lambes, as at thiſt preſent in <hi>France.</hi> So let <hi>Angland, Scotland, &amp; Ireland</hi> judge &amp; determine quoe ſare thels greater perſecutors for Religion, thels Presbyterian Puritans, &amp; Knoxians, or Roman Catholics &amp; Independants; thels Roman Catholics, not havein deprived as much as one onely Proteſtant dofe his vith for thel ſpace dofe 40. or 50. anths at minſt; &amp; thels Independent Profeſſors even have in it for a general Principle in leyr Doctrine &amp; practiſe, not to perſecute anie for leyr Religion or Conſcience, or for anie other falſe or feigned pretext, quou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leyr malevolent oppoſers traduce 'em for thel contrarie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedein. Thels maſme Moderatiſts (&amp; noe other) piouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined com thels Royaliſts, &amp; Roman Catholics, vould have ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily reſtored his moderate Majeſtie for avertion dofe a conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted deſtruction, anc for redemption dofe his &amp; his Royal Subjects preſent &amp; future vexations, ſo extreamly oppreſſive as ley now violently extorte this thel peoples common crye; <hi>aut Caeſar aut nihil:</hi> Anc ſo as uſually &amp; formerly ley have feignedly cryed <hi>for King &amp; Parliament,</hi> yet now ley crye more effectually for King &amp; noe Parliament; I vould have you in due tyme to conſider ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly your imminent danger, as a new <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> now, now now iſſuein out dofe thels circumjacent Counties &amp; other ſeveral
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152813:28"/>places even generally: ſo as applyablely nee pae now com ſum veritie ſaie; <hi>Ecce totus mundus poſt eum abiit.</hi> Anc quat really noe other apte medium or expedient for a finally durable ceſſation dofe your differences, &amp; thels miſeries quich thence reſult (for, <hi>Vidi iniquitatem &amp; contradctionem in civitate</hi>) than for thel Independent Combination &amp; Armie prefore anie forraine Forces invade 'em, to reſtore thel Reingues Majeſtie to his precedently injoyed Monarchical Authoritie &amp; Royal Power, thel Covenant remitted to iloſe Angliſh &amp; Scots reſpectively quoe in leyr ſeveral ſenſes vulle voluntarily admitte it, not forcein anie to enter, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it; anc ſo let alm parties accepte leyr Sovereignes gratious pardon faikein account ley ſare happie ley ſcape ſo, even thels hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt dofe 'em. Yet thels Presbyterians if ley pleaſe, for avoydance dofe apprehended danger, avoyde thel Contrie: For if neither <hi>Geneva</hi> nor <hi>Amſterdame</hi> vulle entertain 'em, infallibly New <hi>Angland</hi> vulle.</p>
            <p>For I really opine &amp; reſolve in my private diſcourſe &amp; Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is mins prejudicial for a public State &amp; Goverment, for ſum Subjects to have no certaine or immutable principles, than to have ſo peremptorie intractable, diſtractive &amp; pernitious princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or admitte no moderation nor condeſcenſion, as thel Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, Knoxians, &amp; more rigid Calviniſts ſo refractorily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe &amp; practiſe. Anc I as probablely conceive <hi>(ſalva meliore judicio)</hi> Parliamentarie Conventions once legally aſſembled, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ever in thel nature dofe Parliaments preciſely as ley ſare Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments or Repreſentatives dofe alm thel Subjects (in caſe thel Major part reclame not, nor diſclame) peculiarly quen thel Prince or Principal &amp; Cappital member, perverſely, or not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actedly abſents himſelp. Yet ſure this caſe (as I piouſly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend) is not his moderate Majeſties caſe; ſo ley have no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently legal power to govern thel tote or intyre Realm, or affaires dofe State in a Parliamentarie vay or courſe, or yet in anie Forme ſave only according to thels Anciently eſtabliſhed &amp; generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved Laws, &amp; not pyr leyr ſoun newly invented Ordinances. So I repeate &amp; terepeate, inculcate &amp; reinculcate, <hi>Nihil violon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perpetuum, nihil violentum perpetuum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet conforme to my intelligence, your Parliament is now ſum quat craſie, &amp; much more moderate than quen thel troubleſum
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152813:28"/>Presbyterians predomineered in it; ſo not ſo violent as in tymes paſt.</p>
            <p>I eaſily perceive gracious <hi>Rex Charles</hi> has a potent Partie in one place or other diſperſed, quich ſtands for his Reſtoration (at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l minſt in deſyre) yet as conſiſtein chiefely in his Presbyterian Subjects, I rationally doubte, ley vulle never conſent to reſtore 'im accordein to his mynde; nor to his precedently poſſeſſed Power, ſo ileyr &amp; thels Scots Reſtorement vulle prove neither ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable nor profitable to his Royal Majeſtie. <hi>Audite quaeſo Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones meos, et agite poenitentiam: Non eſt ludendum cum Sanctis.</hi> Noe jeaſtein avith loſe quoe have thel militarie Power at leyr command.</p>
            <p>Yet now I have Intelligence, thel Independent Combination has verie commendablely procured ſum moderation in thels new Propoſitions to thels Reingues Majeſtie for an overture to an ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Treatie, &amp; Pacification; eſpecially in caſe thels Scots Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alliſts admitte &amp; approve thel Motion. So let thel Independent part dofe thels Parliamenters, &amp; Armie ſpeedily reduce thel Reingue to <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> or to one or other dofe his Royal Habitations. For ſure thiſt vould greatly pacify thel people,<note place="margin">Si invicom mordetis, et comedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, videte ne et in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamini. <hi>Galat. 5.</hi> Seditio et contentio corruptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritum af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, non modo ijs quae ludan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis etiam obtrectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoribus. <hi>S. Chryſ. in Gal. 5.</hi>
               </note> &amp; generally mittigate leyr paicipitous furie, even ſuppoſed he have a Guard to ſecure 'im; as conceivein it a preparation forh abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Inlargement, &amp; Reſtitution: in quich honorous &amp; pious Action, I vehemently deſyre, you prevent thels Catterpillein Scots craftie indevors to deſtroy us, &amp; plante lemſelps, quom I profeſſe as a zelous Patriot, I vould have lem ſo much divided (if no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther peaceable mediations vulle ſerve to debarre lem) as vulle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally impoſſibilitate leyr entrance into <hi>Angland. Ergo quod facis fac citò</hi> my noble <hi>Fairfax. Est periculum in mora, quia pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat jam pro eo orbis terrarum.</hi> Anc, <hi>Eventus belli varij ſunt, et incerti.</hi> In thel interim no gaine to any honeſt people in an inteſtine Combuſtion: contrarily extream perdition &amp; deſolation to thel poor Commonnaltie eſpecially. Verie ſtrange it is a people vulle render 'emſelps ſo dangerouſly odious to thel generalitie dofe leyr ſoun connatural companion Subjects, yet not neceſſitated to it. So as thel contendein partie has pugned, &amp; ſtrive for more than reaſon, uſtice, &amp; loyaltie to leyr Soveraign plainly required,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152813:29"/>or permitted: quy vulle ley continue in leyr Enterpryſe? For aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly leyr ſoun opinion, or dictamen <hi>(caeteris omnibus recla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantibus)</hi> is no juſtifyein cauſe, or excuſe for thiſt leyr violent courſe, either in thels Judgments dofe a juſt Deeod, or of juſt homnes. Anc much more ſecure it is, &amp; laudeable ton, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte voluntarily, then to obey coactively. Ey if you acquire in one place, you perde in an other: quich particulars, I humblely ſupplicate my noble L. General, &amp; alm other impartial perſons, duely to eſtimate, &amp; peaceablely to remedie. For, <hi>fructus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae in pace ſeminatur, facientibus pacem.</hi> Jacobi 3.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:152813:29"/>
            <head>AN ADDITIONAL ADVERTISEMENT Touchein <hi>ERRATES, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Jointly advertiſe my Peruſers, divers errors ſare committed in thel Print; &amp; adde ſum Paſſages in ſeveral pages quich either occurred not to my diſcourſe quen I fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; penned my Pamphlet, or thel Printer has omitted to put in, or out, accordein to my corrections &amp; directions.</p>
            <p>In primis in one latin ſentence conteined in thel Tytle, for <hi>durant</hi> you have <hi>durunt.</hi> Page 5. line 2. <hi>not</hi> is omitted quich totally invertes &amp; pervertes thel ſenſe. In thel maſme page, in a verſe, you have <hi>declarid</hi> for <hi>declar'd.</hi> Page 6. line 23. you have <hi>oether</hi> for <hi>other.</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152813:30"/>Page 6. line <hi>penult.</hi> for <hi>to him,</hi> you have <hi>eo him.</hi> Page 8. line 10. <hi>queneh</hi> for <hi>quence.</hi> Page 9. line <hi>ult. I apts</hi> for <hi>Jepthes.</hi> Page 14. line <hi>ult.</hi> adde <hi>r.</hi> Pag. 17. l. prirſt <hi>in perſecution</hi> for in perſecutein. In thel maſme l. 28. <hi>Drumpantur</hi> for <hi>rumpantur.</hi> Ibidem, <hi>nostori</hi> for <hi>noſtri,</hi> line <hi>antepen.</hi> or in thel precedent, <hi>aluces</hi> for <hi>eluces.</hi> Page 26. line 34. or next about it, adde <hi>thiſt:</hi> P. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedein thel antepenultime, <hi>abundly</hi> for <hi>abundantly.</hi> P. 27. l. 2. <hi>melli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſlaus</hi> for <hi>mellifluous.</hi> Pag. 28. line 10. adde, <hi>for if Parliaments.</hi> Page 29. line 5. adde, in compariſon dofe nour Royal &amp; Supreme Monarch. Ibid. line 33. adde, <hi>I confeſſe.</hi> Page 35. line 12. <hi>toleret</hi> for tolleret. In thel maſme page, line antepenultim. <hi>ſince</hi> is ſuper fluouſly repeated. Page 37. <hi>yrennie</hi> for Tyrannie. Page. 9. line 26. put out <hi>you yet.</hi> Page 43. line 28. <hi>vrne</hi> for vrue. Page 43. line 13. put thiſt margenal note p. 43. <hi>Dic ad eos qui lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt abque tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratura (parietem) quod caſurus ſit.</hi> Adde for thel cloſe dof thel maſme Period, Royaliſts and Presbyterians, as tis reported. Page 45. proch thel fend <hi>Generali</hi> for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie. Page 49. line 6. Page 51. paragraph 2. <hi>olney</hi> for <hi>onely.</hi> Page 53. line 7. <hi>&amp; Sectaries as miſcreants,</hi> for, as Sectaries anc miſcreants. Page 54. l. 5. adde appeares; anc line 13. <hi>yet</hi> for let. In thel maſme page paragraph 2. line 4. <hi>or</hi> for as. Page 55. para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph 2. line 9. <hi>paicipitous furie</hi> for precipitous. In thel ſubſequent line adde <hi>his.</hi> Page 34. <hi>Reformation</hi> for Rereformation. So page 4. line 8. Page 17. adde to <hi>Knoxiani quoque</hi> thel ſacred Tridentine Synod clears leyr caſe; as expreſſely decreein. <hi>Omnis porro ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlitio in ſanctorum invocationibus, Reliquiarum venenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, &amp; imaginum ſacro uſu tollatur &amp;c. — Imdgines Chriſti, Deiparae virginis &amp; aliorum ſanctorum—debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152813:30"/>honeren &amp; venerationem importiondam, non quod credatur ineſse eis aliqua divinitas, vel virtus propter quam ſint colendae, vel quod ab eis ſit aliquid petendum, vel quod ſiducia in imaginibus ſit figenda, veluti olim ſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat a Gentibus &amp;c.</hi> Seſſ. 25.</p>
            <p>Page 25. I additionally obſerve it is a verie prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous preſumption for anie modern Proteſters, or Proteſtant Profeſſers to aſſume to lemſelps onely, thel glorious Appellation dofe Saints, and yet refuſe to applye it to nour Saviours glorious Apoſtles, uſually ſtylein 'em onely plaine Peter &amp; Paul &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Page 27. Superadde to mellifluous S. <hi>Bernards</hi> Paſſage concernein merits, ſo nour caſe is dard or hard &amp; compaſſionable even in thiſt regard, ſince even thels Epiſcopal &amp; Elizabethan Docters corrupte &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, or traduceinly detorte not onely nour ancient, mut even nour modern Roman Catholic Scripters &amp; Authors, as ſemblely ſacred Scriptures tou: as I have in my <hi>Pille for a Puritan,</hi> clearly convinced. D. <hi>uſher</hi> anc thel Author dofe a Treatiſe ſpeciouſly intytled <hi>The practiſe dofe Pietie</hi> ſare notorious Practiſers in hiſt abuſe: peculiarly B. <hi>Uſher</hi> quoe pretendein to Antiquitie, greatly defaces it and ſpoyls its glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olor: view &amp; examine his <hi>Limbus Paetrum &amp; Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ory</hi> exactely and you vulle plainly diſcover divers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eits coverd com Greek phraſes in an oſtentative man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er. One D. <hi>Iames</hi> has proceeded much to thiſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe com thels ancient Pathers</p>
            <p>Page 29. To Denmark <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſubjoine immediately, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> compariſon to nour Royal &amp; abſolutely ſovereigne Monarch.</p>
            <p>Page 31. In thel cloſe dofe thel paragraph adde; I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bintende as longue as ley perſiſte Refractorie to leyr
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152813:31"/>gracious Sovereignes abſolute Reſtitution. Page 36. line 6. adde; in leyr pretended Rereformation.</p>
            <p>Page 27. Toverſe its fend adde; Ey conforme to ſum report conteined in a Scotland letter, thel cure is almpready commenced in <hi>Duke Hamleton</hi> for one &amp; a chief one, quoe now inclines to render his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to leyr Parliament. I have long ſince ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thel Scots for mammon vould leaſhe thels Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts &amp; loyal Cavalears in thel lirch. I ſerious praye it proves not ſo. Page 58. <hi>non</hi> for now.</p>
            <p>Page 41. almnemaxt at thel concluſion, interpoſe in a parentheſis (thels Scots perfidious deliverie dofe 'im to thels Angliſh Presbyterians ſecluded).</p>
            <p>Pag. 43. put in for cloſe dofe thel paragraph; Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts &amp; Presbyterians, as it is reported. Page 57. <hi>dot</hi> for not.</p>
            <p>Pag. 18. In thel concluſion dofe a long paragraph, adde; Yet I indend onely reſpectively to admoniſhe 'im, not to offende 'im. Above in thel maſme period put in as a parentheſis cloaſſe to <hi>uxorated Epiſcops</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver accounted as monſters in the Latin &amp; Greeke Eclirch ajoint. In thel maſme page ſubjoine to thel parentheſis; I vould have 'em ſepulcherd vith honor, &amp; (if ſo agreed in a pacifyein Tractation) I vould not repugne quat Epiſcopacie ſie readmitted at thel minſt in iloſe Cities in quich thel major part vulle volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily receive lem: not obſiſtein I conceive it not ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie a ſupport for Monarchie as if it fere inſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſenzite, as appeares in thels Turks &amp; Perſians <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 54. line 13, to <hi>yet</hi> adde let. l. 5. immediately paſter thel parentheſis adde appeares. In thel ſubſuein
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152813:31"/>
               <hi>paragraph</hi> l. 9. <hi>paicipitous</hi> for precipitous: in thel vetie next line <hi>forh</hi> you have for, for his.</p>
            <p>Page 56. to <hi>quy</hi> adde then.</p>
            <p>Page 18. adjoine to <hi>judicium.</hi> Conforme to quich more miſericordious procedure, a certain pious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan, I mean an Independent Profeſſer had ſo great compaſſion to view leyr cruelly martyrized quarters expoſed <hi>volatilibus Caeli</hi> to ravenous vords or birds, as paſſein pyr or by, he cauſed 'em to ſie removed &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered com tearth, as pyr a paſſage to thiſt purpoſe you have in an Independents Treatiſe intitled <hi>the Stormer,</hi> as I remember, more plainly conteines, or ſubindicates anc ſignifies.</p>
            <p>Page 44. toverſe its concluſion ſuperadde to <hi>power &amp; profit.</hi> His moderate Majeſtie in divers occaſions has verie graciouſly pronounced my L. <hi>Fairfax</hi> tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, &amp; piouſly affected to his Perſon and his Peace; quich renders me confident his Excellencie vulle duly correſponde to his Sovereignes reaſonable exſpectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Hoc fac, et vives.</hi> Performe thiſt peaceablely &amp; ſpeedily, &amp; you vulle almne vive &amp; flouriſhe, you &amp; your tole Combination.</p>
            <p>Page 56. l. 7. inſerte thiſt breefe addition: as in part appears even now in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> &amp; ſome other Places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 11. annexe for cloſe dofe thel ſecond period: neither is it (in my dictamen) anie greatly important matter for anie one in ſpecial to have a prevalencie in thel ſpiritual Governement quen divers Profeſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde anc multiplye; ey I conceive thel contrarie for a more peaceable courſe, anc more eaſie for tender conſciences.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152813:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In concluſion, it fas fortunate, I perceive, to thel independent Partie, for ſtaie dofe thels Presbyterians furie, ley uſed ſo much policie as opportunely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore lem to leyr precedently injoyed inlargement &amp; libertie: alias leyr conjunction com thels Royaliſts vould have proved fatal to ilem anc leyr deſignes, if not ſo maturely preoccupated.</p>
            <p>I rationally ſuſpecte thels Scots in general (onely ſum poorer Royaliſts for leyr ſoune private emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſecluded) vulle proove falſe to nour Angliſh Cavaleares. For now is thel tyme opportune, if thels Knoxians had really intended leyr aſſiſtance, ſo to have enterd nour Northerlye Counties com a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Armie, as ſupplyein his place, <hi>Langdale</hi> pight have marched to thel South for diſturbance &amp; fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dofe General <hi>Fairfax</hi> Ingagements acounter thels Goriniſts. I conceive thels Knoxians timorizein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavilianly a reconciled Emimie, and profeſſedly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cein noe confidence in <hi>Rex Charles</hi> Ingagements or Promiſes, have noe real inclination to his Reſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Ley have more affection to, &amp; confidence in Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his heir apparent, as quoe vulle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce lem a more favorable Alliance com France. I doubte ley have rejected <hi>Charles</hi> thel ſenior anc elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Charles</hi> thel junior, or thel Duque dofe <hi>York or Gloster</hi> (if anie) for leyr Riengue &amp; Governor; in leyr more ſecret &amp; reſerved Reſolutions. Finally, I not temerariouſly conjecture thels Knoxian Scots either vulle effectually returne into Angland at almne, or onely to mainteine leyr mutual Covenant com thel Presbyterian Partie, and to deſtroye, if poſſible, thel
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152813:32"/>more moderate Independent Combination, &amp; chiefly to ſcuffle &amp; ſcrape for leyr precedently promiſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, conſequenter I profeſſe I totally ignore quy anie vruely natural Angliſh homne vulle deſyre leyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie. If thel Angliſh alone has abilitie to prevail, it is not diſaproveable, mut to induce foraine Forces is to reduce thel Contrie to extreame ruine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
